<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations concerning marriage the honour, duties, benefits, troubles of it whereto are added 1. directions in two particulars, 1. how they that have wives may be as if they had none, 2., how to prepare for parting with a dear yoke-fellow by death, or other-wife : 2. resolution of this case of conscience, whether a man may lawfully marry his wives sister? / by Edward Reyner ...</title>
            <author>Reyner, Edward, 1600-1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3111</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13451855</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13451855</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99599</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99599)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 474:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations concerning marriage the honour, duties, benefits, troubles of it whereto are added 1. directions in two particulars, 1. how they that have wives may be as if they had none, 2., how to prepare for parting with a dear yoke-fellow by death, or other-wife : 2. resolution of this case of conscience, whether a man may lawfully marry his wives sister? / by Edward Reyner ...</title>
                  <author>Reyner, Edward, 1600-1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 87 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. T. for Thomas Newbery ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: 7th prelim. leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage with deceased wife's sister --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Marriage --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99599:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99599:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONSIDERATIONS Concerning MARRIAGE, The HONOUR, DUTIES, BENEFITS, TROUBLES of it.</p>
            <p>Whereto are added,
<list>
                  <item>1. Directions in two Particulars.
<list>
                        <item>1. How they that have wives may be as if they had none.</item>
                        <item>2 How to prepare for part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a dear yoke-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low by death, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Reſolution of this Caſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Whether a man may lawfully marry his Wives Siſter?</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By EDWARD REYNER, Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. T.</hi> for <hi>Thomas New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery,</hi> and are to be ſold at the three <hi>Golden Lions</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> neer the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> MDCLVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99599:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99599:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou mayeſt wonder that I ſhould bring this poor Embryo to the birth, in the Preſſe, the place of bringing forth. When I firſt penn'd theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe conſiderations concerning marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, I had not the leaſt thought that they ſhould have ſeen more light, then came in at my Study-window; or that any more eyes then mine own, ſhould have ſeen them, while I lived. But thus it came to paſſe; Theſe being the heads of what I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in private at the Marriage of
<pb facs="tcp:99599:3"/>ſome Friends not long ago; and I being requeſted ſoon after to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate my Notes thereof, reveiw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, but found them very ſhort and imperfect, and that what I had written could not give an account, of what God helped me then to ſpeak. Hereupon I reſolved to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe and inlarge them a little, onely that I might get ſome Copies written out, to gratifie ſome Friends that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired them. But when I had almoſt finiſhed them, I had ſeveral Hints upon my Heart from Providentiall occurences to expoſe them to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick view: Whereto I was alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by ſome godly and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous friends, who had the peruſal of them. Thus I am drawn to hope, that through Gods bleſſing (which can make little Pamphlets inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental for the good of others, as well as great volumes) this little, poor, plain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iece, may be of uſe to many, becauſe,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Subject of this Diſcourſe, to vvit, Marriage, is of general ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and of ſpeciall conſequences,
<pb facs="tcp:99599:3"/>for it is the firſt Relation and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of humane Society; and it is the Rule and Meaſure of the Wel-orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all other Relations, and hath a Regulating Influence upon them all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Principall Concernments of Marriage (as I humbly conceive) are plainly declared, briefly compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed and uſefully applyed herein.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Tract, being ſo ſmall, may be bought cheap, and read ſoon; and be ready to direct either Poor or Rich, vvho deſire to vvalk by Rule in their Matrimonial State.</p>
            <p>The Lord command his Bleſſing upon it, that it may be effectual, and proſper in the things vvhereto I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it, and Gods Providence ſends it novv unto thee; even to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the good pleaſure of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards thee, in making thy Relations religious in the manner and order of them, and ſweet and comfortable to thee in the end and uſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Reader, I pray thee live this book throughly in thy family, I hope it may draw down a bleſſing upon thy
<pb facs="tcp:99599:4"/>whole houſe; when thou reapeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by this, or any other Tract, give God the praiſe, and let the Author have thy prayers to God to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him and bleſs him in his labors. Which is the requeſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 19. 1657.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Of thy Friend in the Lord,</hi> Edw. Reyner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99599:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He worthy Author of this enſuing Treatiſe, was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, not onely to favour me, with the peruſal of it, but alſo to put ſo much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon me, as to crave my Judgement concerning it, before he purpoſed to make it publick. Doubtleſs ſuch condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his ſpirit, unto a friend, every way inferiour to himſelf, do ſpeak his great humility, which addeth much lustre un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the rich abilities, with which the Lord hath crowned him: His former
<pb facs="tcp:99599:5"/>practical pieces, have found ſo good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance amongst gracious ſavorie ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited Christians, that the prefixing of his Name, will be ſufficient commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this book. Whoſoever have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore drunk of his rich ſpiritul Wines, will ſay, There is no need to hang forth an Ivy-buſh to call in Cuſtomers, when his veſſels are broached. I do ingeniouſly profeſs, that I have received edification, by reading over this diſcourſe, and thence I take encouragement to commend it to thy ſerious peruſal.</p>
            <p>Long ſince, when I read Reverend Mr. <hi>Greenhams Treatiſe of a Contract, before Marriage,</hi> and obſerved his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inſtructing of the perſons contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, in the Articles of faith, and the ten commandements, I then thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in mine own thoughts; Surely this man of God, judged that this condition of life, doth need more than ordinary helps, that it might be Chriſtianly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged. And queſtionleſs upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:99599:5"/>(not excluding others) Miniſters moſt eminently godly, have in their times perſwaded a matrimonial contract, before the conſummation of Marriage, that the perſons intending that change, might by peculiar advice and prayer, be prepared for it. I well remember, that my good Friend Mr. <hi>John Ball,</hi> (whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is precious) during the time of his laſt ſickneſs, did often ſpeak to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; <hi>If God ſhould be pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore me to the exerciſe of my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, I will more preach and preſſe Relative duties, then I have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done.</hi> The power of godlineſs, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in relations, and what relation is ſo influential as this, betwixt husband and wife. This is the first and fundamental human Relation, and according to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and converſation of husband and wife in their domeſtical ſtate and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, will the behavior of children, ſervants, and others in the family, be uſually ordered, both amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb facs="tcp:99599:6"/>in their mutual ſubordinations, and towards others occaſionally. I know that many of Gods <hi>Worthies,</hi> both in former and latter times, have in their Diſcourſes concerning domeſtical duties, mentioned many things here particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, yet as the concurrence of Brethren addeth ſtrength to their counſel, ſo that which is additional, may be found pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. In mine apprehenſion, there is a vein of Scripture ſtrength, and evidence together with the ſavorineſs and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Authors Spirit running through the whole book from beginning to end: in theſe regards I was moved to requeſt him, to make it publick, hoping that it will (through Gods bleſſing) be inſtrumental, in promoting the power of godlineſs, amongſt profeſſors of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. That caſe of conſcience which is added unto the practical diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Marriage, is upon diſpute, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined with ſo much ſtrength and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, both <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane,</hi> that I
<pb facs="tcp:99599:6"/>am perſwaded, much ſin in that kinde, will hereby, for the future be prevented. There were three ſheets more prepared for the Preſs, concerning the mutual ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual communion, betwixt Chriſt, and the ſoul, which is eſpouſed to him, whereof there are ſome ſhort hints, in page <hi>42.</hi> and <hi>43.</hi> and <hi>44.</hi> and <hi>60.</hi> of the following Treatiſe; and doubtleſs this piece would have been acceptable, and profitable unto Chriſt-improving Chriſtians; This was wrapped up in a paper, directed unto me, and ſent by a ſpecial friend, who loſt it out of his pocket, in his journey from <hi>Lincoln</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> in <hi>May</hi> laſt. This loſs is the more to be lamented, becauſe the Author hath no copy of it. There have been hitherto, ſome expectations that this loſs might have been recovered, that this ſpiritual Tract might have been added unto the former, but now through long diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, our hopes grow more faint. If hereafter Gods good hand of providence,
<pb facs="tcp:99599:7"/>ſhould bring this Manuſcript, either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Author at <hi>Lincoln,</hi> or to my ſelf at <hi>London,</hi> the Reſtorer thereof, ſhould be well recompenced, and it ſhould be forthwith publiſhed for common profit. Chriſtian Reader, as the Author deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, ſo he beggeth, thy Prayers, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octo. 15. 1657.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Friend and Servant in Chriſt,</hi> Simeon Aſhe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:99599:7"/>
            <head>Let the Reader be deſired to amend theſe faults with his pen before he peruſe the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ok.</head>
            <head type="sub">ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. Line 4. for efficiency read <hi>efficient:</hi> p 2. l. 6. f juſtification r. <hi>inſtitution</hi> p. 5 l. 13 f Love r. <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</hi> p. 6. l. 9. r. <hi>to act in to his Church:</hi> p. 6. l. 32. f. ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification r. <hi>inſtitution:</hi> p. 8 l. 9 f. Lincy r <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey.</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, r. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. p. 14 in marg. Col. 18. 3. r <hi>Col.</hi> 3 18. p. 15. l. <hi>ult.</hi> l is, r. <hi>in the ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> p 18. l. 17. f follows r. <hi>flons,</hi> p. 23 l. 25 f Proprietors, r. <hi>Proprietaries:</hi> p. 25 l 3. f ſpiritual r <hi>ſpecial</hi> p. 25 l. 5 f. walking, r. <hi>wel-being:</hi> p. 26. l. 19 f. ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance r. <hi>clean,</hi> marg. r. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. 2. p. 26. l. 34. f. communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on r <hi>communication:</hi> p. 27. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. f. parties. r. <hi>partie,</hi> &amp; l. 26. f. <hi>it is,</hi> r. <hi>and is apteſt.</hi> &amp; l 32. f heaven 1 <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers:</hi> p 30. l. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> f. allunder, r <hi>aſunder</hi> &amp; l. 2. f con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, r. <hi>contentation.</hi> &amp; l. 16. f. wreſt, r <hi>wreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le,</hi> &amp; l. 19. put out <hi>is:</hi> p 31. marg. r 1 Tim. 5 14. f. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 14. p. 33. l. 26. f. covenant, r. <hi>government,</hi> &amp; l. 30 f. exerciſes. r. <hi>exerciſe:</hi> p. 44. l. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> r. <hi>to thriſt:</hi> p. 53. l. 13 f. fore-arned, r. <hi>fore-armed:</hi> p. 59. l. 3. f. our r. <hi>or,</hi> &amp; l. 28. f. ours, r. <hi>our:</hi> p. 60 l 3. f. learn r <hi>leave:</hi> p. 64. l. 29. f. word, r. <hi>world.</hi> p. 70. l. 3. f. fitted, r. <hi>filled.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99599:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99599:8"/>
            <head>THE HONOUR OF MARIAGE. There be four things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in it.</head>
            <p>The
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Honour</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Duties</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Benefits</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Troubles</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> of it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The Honour of Mariage.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ariage is honourable, in all</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) of high eſteem and great account among all ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, high and low; rich and poor. <hi>and the bed</hi> (conſidered in it ſelf)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99599:9"/>
                  <hi>is undefiled. Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> might have uſed it in their Innocencie. This is common to all mankind.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. from the Author.</note>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. From the efficiency or Author of it, that is God, 5 wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1 By juſtification. Mariage is <hi>Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance;</hi> he firſt invented it and appointed it. What is of God is excellent and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By adminiſtration, he maried <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve.</hi> When he had builded the rib he took out of the mans ſide into a woman,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.22.</note> 
                  <hi>he brought her to the man,</hi> that is, joyned her in mariage with him, and God is ſaid, now to joyn man and wife together, <hi>Math.</hi> 19.6. that is, by his ordinance, and by his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
               <p n="3">3 By Qualification of the Perſons for a Matrimonial Relation;
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.</note> making the woman to be <hi>a help meet for the man;</hi> and the Man to be a fit head and guide, for the woman. This is Gods work, <hi>A prudent wife is from the Lord. Prov.</hi> 19.14. So is a loving Husband. God makes them ſo.</p>
               <p n="4">4 By Benediction, God bleſſeth them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to make them partakers of al the Ends and comforts of mariage. As he did <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> when he had made them and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.28. Gen. 33 5.</note> he pronounced a large bleſſing upon them, ſaying, <hi>Be fruitful and multiply and repleniſh the earth.</hi> Children, and famlies. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 107.41. are Gods gifts.</p>
               <p n="5">5 By Miſſion of his Angels, which God ſends forth to be miniſtring ſpirits to his ſervants for aſſiſtance in this buſineſs; as to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99599:9"/>Servant, when his Maſter ſent him to <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> to take a wife unto his ſon <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and to <hi>Ioſeph, Mary's</hi> Eſpouſed husband,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.7.21.40. Math. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 1.20. and 2.13. The Miniſtry of Angels about mariage (by Direction and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection) implyes it to be weighty and worthy in it ſelf, though unto many it ſeemeth Worldly and baſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reaſ. 2. from the ſubject and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</note>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. From the Subject and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of mariage at the firſt. Who were the firſt couple whom God maried? <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> who were the common Parents of all Man-kind; of all the Kings, Queens, Princes and Nobles in the world; yea of Jeſus Chriſt according to the fleſh. Even he was <hi>The Son of Adam, Luke</hi> 3.38.</p>
               <p>Where was mariage firſt Celebrated? <hi>In paradiſe,</hi> where God manifeſted his preſence to our firſt Parents; which made the place a Heaven upon Earth.</p>
               <p>When was mariage firſt inſtituted and miniſtred? <hi>In the time of mans Innocency,</hi> before his fall. Before ſin entred into the world. Therefore there is no ſin in Mariage; but mariage is now a Remedy againſt ſin.</p>
               <p>The perſons, place and Time of the firſt mariage, or of mariage at the firſt, doe put Honour upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reaſ. 3 From Jeſus Chriſt.</note>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. From Jeſus Chriſt who highly honoured mariage, not onely by chuſing to be conceived and born of a woman Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed to a man; and by his preſence at that mariage in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> where <hi>he wrought his firſt miracle,
<note place="margin">John. 2.1, 2, 10.11.</note> and manifeſted forth his Glory by</hi> turning water into wine; and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99599:10"/>the kingdom of Heaven to <hi>a weddin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> feaſt.</hi> But eſpecially by chuſing a Conjugal Relation to ſtand in to his Church (as hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to wife) and therein
<list>
                     <item>1. To manifeſt and Communicate himſelf to her.</item>
                     <item>2. To ſolace and delight himſelf with her.</item>
                     <item>3. To gloryfie himſelf in her; and her with himſelf for ever in Heaven.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>This mariage is begun between Chriſt and his Church and every true believer in Eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal upon Earth, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. and it is conſummated in Heaven, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.7, 8, 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed are they which are called to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-ſupper of the Lamb;</hi> that is as ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it, the Time of Celeſtial Joyes.</p>
               <p>Hence the Civil mariage between man and wife is made by <hi>Paul,</hi> a figure or repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Myſtical Mariage between Chriſt and his Church, and every childe of God; in reſpect of the union, or neer conjunction of them. (<hi>This is now bone of my bone and fleſh of my fleſh,</hi> ſaid <hi>Adam</hi> of his wife, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2 23. <hi>we are members of his</hi> (that is Chriſts) <hi>body, of his fleſh, and of his bones,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> of Saints and Beleivers, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.30. and of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal Communion between them. Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> concludes verſe 32. <hi>This is a great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, but I ſpeak concerning Chriſt and the Church:</hi> as if he had ſaid, All I have written concerning husband and Wife, ſets forth the Matrimonial Relation and fellowſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and his Church, his expreſſions
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99599:10"/>of love to her; and interchangeably her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to him.</p>
               <p>Let me adde, Is it not an honour to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage that a moſt ſweet choice Piece of Scripture was indited by the Holy Ghoſt, as an Epithalamium or Mariage-ſong, called <hi>The Song of Songs,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">Cant. 1.1.</note> of all ſongs the moſt excellent, becauſe it celebrateth the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Mariage between Chriſt and the Church; and poureth forth a Torrent of Spiritual love that is between them. The forty and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th Pſalm is of the ſame ſubject, <hi>A Pſalm of Love,</hi> or Mariage-Hymn, ſetting forth Chriſt the bridegroom in his Glory; and the Church his ſpouſe in her beauty.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> General con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</note>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. From General Conſent and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, which (as ſome obſerve) hath ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mariage in Dignity and Honour:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Regers</hi> of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> and graced it with Priviledges, and granted Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities to it far above ſingle life, both in war and peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Slight not Mariage.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Think not ſlightly of Mariage as a low contemptible thing; but highly, as a Solemn Ordinance of God, of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and Importance to you; wherein the future Comfort of your Lives is bound up. Therefore enter not raſhly into it, but advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly with due conſideration for the choiſe of a fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yoke-fellow.
<note place="margin">Prov. 20.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Every purpoſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) is eſtabliſhed by Counſel, and with good advice make war.</hi> I may adde, with good advice ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y: becauſe Mariage is not upon liking (<hi>God hates putting away, Mala.</hi> 2.16) but for life. It is the tying of ſuch a knot as nothing but death can looſe: it is a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99599:11"/>buſineſſe of laſting importance. An Errour therein may prove dangerous. Shall we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that Relation or condition mean or inconſiderable, whereof God himſelf was the Inſtitutor and Miniſter? <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> the firſt couple? and Paradiſe the place where, and Innocency the ſtate or Time when Mariage was celebrated at firſt? which Chriſt hath choſen to act into his Church unto Eternity?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of it.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Then Husbands and Wives ſhould preſerve the Honour of Mariage in their Carriage; and not blemiſh or ſtain the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it, Either</p>
               <p n="1">1. By being light, vain, looſe, frolick in their ſpirits or demeanour, for that is a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Gravity of Mariage.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or by being froward, peeviſh, proud, ſullen, diſcontented, impatient, diſdainful in their ſpirits or carriage; for that is a diſhonour to the Amity, Suavity and Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Mariage.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or by unfaithfulneſſe and bodily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, embracing the boſoms of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; for that is a diſhonour to the Unity, Purity, Chaſtity of Mariage. <hi>Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 13.4.</note> if Magiſtrates do not.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Or by loving any other man or woman in a conjugal way, better then his own wife, or her own Husband. This is a diſhonour to Gods Juſtification of mariage and to the mariage-bond and covenant; which tieth Husband and wife, to forſake all others, in this way; and to cleave in love one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99599:11"/>inſeparably, till death.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 3. Honour God in mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 3 Then, take Care and indeavour to honour God, in your Mariage, by <hi>marying in the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.39. and 11.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What is it to marry in the Lord?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To make God the beginning and end of our Mariage.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The beginning of it,
<note place="margin">Make God the beginning of Mariage.</note> by ſeeking ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to God for councel &amp; direction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: for guidance of our Affection to a right object; for the choice of a fit yoak-fellow: for making the Woman a Comfortable help, and the man a ſutable Head; expecting to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive one another, as a ſpecial giſt and token of favour from the hand of God. For <hi>who findeth a wiſe, findeth a good thing and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth favour of the Lord,</hi> ſaith Solomon, <note place="margin">Prov. 18.22. Prov. 19.14.</note> And, <hi>Houſe and riches are the Inheritance of fathers</hi> (a man may have a woman and a portion from her father) <hi>but a prudent wife</hi> (or the Qualifications of a woman to make her a wife) <hi>is from the Lord:</hi> the ſame may be ſaid of the man. Alſo, by looking chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at or for the grace of God, one in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the load-ſtone of our love, and the inkindler of our affections each to other. Look more at inward goodneſs then at out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward goods or beauty: eſpecially at ſutable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Religion, <hi>Be ye not unequally yoked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with unbelievers,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. Do not mary with Idolaters or Infidels, this is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as when beaſts of diverſe kinds draw together; an ox and an aſſe might not be coupled together in the law.
<note place="margin">Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 22.10.</note> We ſhould be affraid to yoke our ſelves with any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99599:12"/>heifers or bullocks, that will not bear Chriſts yoke. We ſhould let Religion have a Negative voice in our choice, that is not to mary any who are not really, or hopefully religious. When perſons match themſelves to thoſe that are either profane and of no reglion, or of falſe and contrary Religions; then their wedding garment (as one ſaith) is made of Lincy wolſey,
<note place="margin">Deut. 22.11.</note> and the wedding Ground is plowed with an Ox and an Aſſe. Such mongrel mariages brought deſtruction upon the old world, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2, 3. God forbids ſuch ungodly matches, <hi>Deut.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 26.35. chap. 27.46.</note> 7.3, 4. <hi>Eſaus</hi> marying the daughter of the <hi>Canaanites</hi> was a great grief of minde to his father and mother, and made <hi>Rebekah</hi> weary of her life. If <hi>Moſes</hi> mary an <hi>Ethiopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> he cannot change her colour or her Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: ſhe will be a vexation to him. Wo to <hi>Sampſon,</hi> if he mary a <hi>Philistine</hi> though he was the ſtrongeſt man. If <hi>Solomon</hi> mary Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous wives they will turn away his heart after other Gods, though he was the wiſeſt man upon earth.
<note place="margin">Kings. 11.1.3, 4:</note>
               </p>
               <p>To marry unequally, as a wiſe man to a fooliſh woman; or a vertuous woman to a profane wicked man,
<note place="margin">Charron.</note> is, as one ſaith, to binde the living to the dead; which was the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Death invented by Tyrants, to make the living languiſh and die by the company of the dead.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To make God the end of our Mariage,
<note place="margin">Make God the end of mariage</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 by propounding Gods glory as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal end of all our Mariage-comforts and enjoyments.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99599:12"/>
               <p n="2">2 By ordering our whole Carriage in that Matrimonial ſtate, according to the rule of Gods word.</p>
               <p n="3">3 By depending on God for his preſence therein, and bleſſing thereon.</p>
               <p n="4">4 By improving mariage, to promote our ſerving of God, and the ſaving of our own ſouls:</p>
               <p>But more of theſe in the next thing to be confidered in Mariage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99599:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The Duties of Mariage.</head>
               <p>WHich are.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Special, of the one Party to the other.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Or common to both, and to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by both, joyntly and mutually.</p>
               <p n="1">1
<note place="margin">1 Special du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to wiſe 6.1. Love.</note> The ſpecial Duties of husband to wife are theſe. 6.</p>
               <p n="1">1 A love to her, which ſhould be, pure, chaſte, ſincere, intire, conſtant. The Husband ſhould love his wife.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 As Chriſt loved his Church, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.</item>
                  <item>2 As the man loveth his own body, <hi>ver.</hi> 28.</item>
                  <item>3 As he loveth himſelf, his whole ſelf, <hi>ver.</hi> 33.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As <hi>Iſaac loved Rebekah, Gen.</hi> 24, 67.</p>
               <p>This duty of Love, comprehends all the reſt: becauſe all, whatſoever the Husband ſaith or doth to his wife, ſhould ſpring from Love, and taſte of love. She ſhould be dear to him as himſelf, and lie as a Lamb in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom.
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Jacob</hi> was content to ſerve a double ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſhip under a Churliſh Maſter, for <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi> to be his wife,
<note place="margin">Gen. 29.32.</note> becauſe he loved her more then <hi>Leah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">2. Tenderneſs.</note> Dutie of the Husband is Tenderneſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99599:13"/>and kindneſs, to nouriſh and cheriſh her, as the more tender part of himſelf, as a man doth his own fleſh; yea as Chriſt doth the Church:
<note place="margin">Eph. 5 29.</note> to ſupply her with Neceſſaries and Conveniences; and ſuffer her to want nothing that is fit for her, and to cover her weakneſſes. Then <hi>Husbands muſt not be bitter to their wives</hi> nor injurious, nor vexations, not make drudges of them.
<note place="margin">Col. 3.19.</note> Their Authority ſhould ſavour more of loving reſpect to them then of rigorous power. Husbands ſhould exerciſe ſo ſweet and amiable a Government over their wives, ſo as not onely their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but alſo their wills and hearts may be ſubject unto them. When Husbands cauſe their wives to go to God with tears, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of their unkindneſs and harſhneſs to them, God will regard and receive their offerings no more.
<note place="margin">Mal. 2.13. <hi>ver.</hi> 14.</note> To this end the Husband ſhould conſider, his wife is his <hi>companion and the wife of his Covenant,</hi> made of a rib taken out of his ſide, not of a bone taken out of his foot, therefore he muſt not tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon her; and ſhe is to be in a ſtate but of Collateral ſubjection to him. She is his <hi>yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow,</hi> that ſtands on even ground with him, and draws on the left ſide. He ſhould make her yoke as eaſy as may be; and not ſuffer the heavier end to lie on her Neck, becauſe ſhe is the weaker veſsel.</p>
               <p n="3">3
<note place="margin">3 Honour 1 Pet. 3.7.</note> Dutie, is due Reſpect and Honour to her, <hi>Peter</hi> gives 3 reaſons for it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The wife is the weaker veſſel therefore ſhe muſt be carefully and gently handled, as a chryſtal glaſs.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99599:14"/>
               <p n="2">2. The wife is <hi>coheir</hi> with her Husband of the grace of life, that is of the life of Grace and glory.</p>
               <p>For (as one obſerves) ſouls have no Sexes; and as they are in Chriſt they are both equal, male and female are in him all one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That their prayers be not hindred.</hi> A Husbands diſreſpect to his wife breeds diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content between them, diſtractions in the familie, and interruptions in duties, and a contempt of them both. To which I may adde that of <hi>Solomon,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pron.</hi> 12.4.</note> A vertuous woman is a crown to her Husband.</hi> and if ſhe give him a crown, he may afford to give her honour. A Husband by debaſing and diſgracing his wife, diſhonoureth himſelf.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">4. Inſtruction</note> Duty of the Husband to the wife, is Inſtruction, Direction, and conſolation, to teach her, counſel her, lead and comfort her, as <hi>her head</hi> (<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.23.) and <hi>Guide, Prov.</hi> 2.17. This is to <hi>dwell with her according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 7. Hence the wife ſhould <hi>learn of her Husbands</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34, 35. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12. A Husband may put honour upon his wife by hearkening to her Counſel, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing the ſame: which is his Dutie when ſhe adviſeth and perſwades him to good; or diſſwades him from Evil. This may be a great advantage to him. For God ſometimes gifteth and graceth the wife equally or above the Husband, as he did <hi>Abigail</hi> above <hi>Nabal,</hi> for he was a fool. <hi>In all that Sarah hath ſaid unto thee hearken unto her voice,</hi> ſaid God to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 21.12. So did <hi>Elkanah</hi> to <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1 22, 23. and <hi>David</hi> heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99599:14"/>to <hi>Abigails</hi> Advice, before ſhe was his wife; how thankful was he both to God and to her for it, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.32. to 35. <hi>Manoah</hi> did the like to his wife, <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.22, 23.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <note place="margin">5. Adheſion.</note> Duty is cleaving to her, forſaking fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, and his deareſt friends for her, and to be glued to her, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one with her, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.31. <hi>One fleſh,</hi> to dwell with her, not onely one houſe, but one bed ſhould hold them. And to rejoyce in her, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.9. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.18.19. or live joyfully with her, make her his <hi>Chepthzibah: and be raviſhed alway with her love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The wife ſhould be as dear to the Husband as <hi>the Hind is to the Hart,</hi> as the Doe to the Roe-buck, This will make him drink waters out of his own Ciſterne onely. Not the having of a wife, but to delight in her and lovingly to comport with her, will keep a man chaſte from embracing the boſom of a ſtranger, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.19, 20. A man ſhould count all others ſtrange women in compariſon of a wife.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <note place="margin">6. Protection</note> Duty is protection of his wife from wrongs and dangers, to reſcue her, if in jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy (as <hi>David</hi> did his wiſes, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.18.) and to right her, if injured. <hi>Abraham</hi> was to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> for <hi>a Covering of the Eyes,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">Gen. 20.16.</note> her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to defend her from injury. <hi>Booz</hi> was to take <hi>Ruth</hi> into his protection as the hen her chickens under her wings, ſignifyed by <hi>ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his ſkirt over her, Ruth.</hi> 3.9. and 2.12. that ſhe might be ſafe under the wings of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. A man giveth Coverture; no action is brought againſt the wife, the man is to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99599:15"/>anſwer, ſhe goeth Covert baron, as is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Therefore woman was made of a bone from under the Mans Arme, that he might be a protection and defence to her. The Husband muſt be as a houſe ſide for his wife, as the fruitful vine to ſpread her ſelf on, to ſupport and ſtrengthen her, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 128.3. and a reſt to give her a ſafe and ſetled abode, <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2. Duties of wife to hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. 6.</note> The Duties of the Wife to the Husband are theſe ſix.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Submiſion.</note>Firſt, Submiſſion to his Authority, and to his juſt and aequal commands, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.1.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>As unto the Lord, Epheſ.</hi> 5.22. as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to deal with God, whoſe Ordinance this is, that the wife ſhould live in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to her own Husband, and that for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake:
<note place="margin">Col. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3</note> 
                  <hi>This is fit in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>As the Church is ſubject unto Christ, Eph.</hi> 5.24. that is freely, willingly, reverently, conſtantly and univerſally in all things.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle giveth four Reaſons of the womans ſubjection to the man, or ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to him, and dependance on him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe ſhe was made <hi>out of man, ſcil.</hi> of a rib taken out of his ſide, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8. <hi>The man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>is not of the woman</hi> (he was made at firſt of the earth) <hi>but the woman</hi> was made <hi>of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The woman was made <hi>for the man</hi> at firſt, not <hi>the man for the woman,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.9. <hi>I will make him</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>a help meet for him, Gen.</hi> 2.18. to ſerve and obey him as her Superior. Hence it is ſaid, that the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99599:15"/>woman is <hi>Vir Occaſionatus:</hi> a man occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, a mans Occaſion, or the Occaſion of a man to ſerve as an aid and as a Second to man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The woman was made <hi>after the man; for Adam was first formed, then Eve,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The woman was firſt in the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> She was firſt deceived by the Serpent, then ſhe drew her Husband into the ſame deception; hereby ſhe was the cauſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of ſin, and ruine to all mankinde: and though ſhe was given to be a help to man, yet ſhe proved at firſt to be a great hurt and hindrance to him. From this priority and cauſality of the woman in ſin, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle infers and preſſeth ſubjection and ſilence upon her to the man, <hi>and not to uſurp Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over the man,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12, 14. upon this account ſhe was more ſtraitly ſubjected to her Husband. For this was inflicted as a chaſtiſement for ſin upon the woman,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16.</note> that her deſire ſhould be ſubject to her Husband, &amp; he ſhould ruleover her: which implies, as ſome obſerve, a further Rule then man had over her by Creation; and with more trouble and grief unto woman-kinde: So that the yoke is now become to her more hard and heavy to be borne.</p>
               <p>Women may Object,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> That was <hi>Eves</hi> fault to be deceived by the Serpent, and to be firſt in the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, not ours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. Eves</hi> puniſhment is yours, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her fault is yours. Her peculiar ſin is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99599:16"/>the fall (diſtinct from <hi>Adams</hi>) is juſtly imputed to you, or elſe her particular puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (diſtinct from <hi>Adams</hi>) is unjuſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon you. <hi>Eves</hi> fault is as much yours, as <hi>Adams</hi> ſin is ours.</p>
               <p>This ſubjection of the wife to the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was the ground of <hi>the womans wearing a vail</hi> or covering, as a ſign ſhe is under the power and Authority of her Husband, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.9, 10. and ſubject to him. <hi>Rebekah</hi> took a vail and covered her ſelf when ſhe ſaw <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac, Gen.</hi> 24.65.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſhe was made out of the ſide, not of the head, that ſhe might be under him, not above him in place and power, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> obeyed <hi>Abraham,</hi> whoſe daughters all obedient wives are, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. And <hi>the holy women in old Time who truſted in God, were in ſubjection to their own Huſbands, to v.</hi> 5. and thoſe wives that are not obedient to their Husbands, are not good, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.5. In this ſence (as ſome conceive) the woman is ſaid to be <hi>The Glory of the man,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7. ſcil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>by her ſubjection, when ſhe obeyes her Husband, as man is the glory of God when he obeyes God. This is the firſt Duty of the wife, Submiſſion, a Comely Leſson for her to learn. Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in a wife is a fault even in a Queen, much greater in a meaner woman, even among Heathens, much more among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that are better taught, as in Queen <hi>Vaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, Eſther,</hi> 1.12.20.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2. Reverence. Eph. 5.33.</note> Duty of the wife is Reverence to her husbands perſon, all due reſpect to him, as her head, in word and deed, in geſture and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99599:16"/>deportment. Even as <hi>Sarah obeyed Abraham and called him Lord.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.6. ſhe is (as one ſaith) crowned and chronicl'd for it. <hi>Michal</hi> mocked her Husband <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.21, 23.</note> and God ſmote her with barrenneſs for it, ſhe was childleſs to her death. The wiſes reverential reſpect to her husband is an honour to him, and an Ornament to her ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3. Helpfulnes.</note> Duty is Helpfulneſs to her Husband in every thing, in his body to cheriſh that, in his ſoul to tender that, in his family to order that; in his Eſtate to get, at leaſt to ſave and to diſpoſe that aright. not to ſpend or waſte the ſame; in his calling and affairs to promote them; in his Name and Credit to preſerve that: in his ſecrets to lock them up in her boſom. She ought to be a Help to him in every thing, a hinderance in nothing. Elſe ſhe is <hi>a woman, but not a wife,</hi> and he that findes her doth not find a good thing, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.22. The wife ſhould cheriſh her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band as the better part of her ſelf. For this very end God made her for man, and maried her to man, to be a help meet for him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.18. If ſhe be not a meet help for the man, ſhee will not pleaſe, ſatisfie and give content. A wife is like a garment though the cloath its made of be very good, yet if it do not fit us, it will not pleaſe us, it wil be uneaſy or uncomely we take no delight to wear it: Conveniency cauſeth contenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If the wife be no meet help ſhaped and cut out as it were of purpoſe for the man to fit and ſute him every way in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition converſation, and occaſions ſhe will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99599:17"/>not ſit cloſe to the man, as a garment doth to the body that fits it, but hang looſe, or be ready to fall off and rather hinder then fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him: and not be an Ornament to him. I commend <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. from 10. to the end, as a Glaſs for all that would be good wives to look and dreſs themſelves in, or as a pattern to imitate, or Rule to walk by every day. <hi>A vertuous woman will do her husband good and not evil all the days of her life, &amp;c.</hi> approve her ſelf faithful to him in every thing, that <hi>his heart may truſt ſafely in her.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 31.11, 12.</note> For Mariage is <hi>Conjugium, the fellowſhip of a yoak,</hi> wherein the wife muſt bear one end, and draw equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with her husband.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">4. Chaſtity Tit. 2.5.</note> Duty is Chaſtity of Converſation (which followes from chaſtity of affection and diſpoſition in the heart) wives muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain, not onely from all acts, but from all Appearances of lightneſs, wantonneſſe, dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance or unfaithfulneſs; that their husbands who caſt off ordinances and holy duties, may, by the holy and chaſte converſation of their wives, be gained to the Lord; to have a liking and good opinion of the Goſpel and the wayes of Chriſt in which they walk, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1, 2. This ſhould be the wiſes deſign upon her husband.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <note place="margin">5. Fear.</note> Duty is Conjugal feare of offending or diſpleaſing her husband. <hi>She that is maried</hi> (Saith Paul) <hi>careth for the things of the world, how ſhe may pleaſe her husband,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34. Wives ſhould couple chaſtity with fear in their carriage to their husbands, not to croſs, or vex, or greive them.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99599:17"/>
               <p n="6">6. <note place="margin">6 Modeſty.</note> Duty of a wife is modeſty, of Apparel and of behaviour. 1 Of Apparel,
<note place="margin">1 of Apparel.</note> not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect coſtly, gaudy attire, new fangled fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, or to go above her rank, or to give way to pride, vanity, exceſs therein: or to account outward adorning, as plaiting of the haire, or wearing of Gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or deck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body, her chiefe Ornament, but,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>A meek and quiet ſpirit</hi> (the frame of the hidden man of the heart) <hi>which is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, which is of great price in the ſight of God,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. and a great Ornament in the ſight of men. <hi>For after this manner in the Old Time the holy women who trusted in God and were in ſubjection to their own Husbands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned themſelves,</hi> verſ. 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.8, 9, 10.</note> 
                  <hi>And good works. I will,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, that women adorn themſelves in modeſt apparel, with ſhamefaſtneſs and ſobriety, not with broidered hair, or gold, pearls or coſtly aray; But which become women profeſſing Godlineſs, with good works.</hi> Both <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in a Comparative ſenſe, that womens adorning ſhould be, not ſo much in outward attire, as in inward vertues, or rather in the latter then in the former. Even Godly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may wear Gold, and jewels, and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, and good attire, as <hi>Rebekah</hi> did the earring and bracelets which <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant put upon her,
<note place="margin">Gen. 24.30, 47.</note> with theſe limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That theſe be ſutable to their rank, place and ſtate, and not coſtly above their ability, and as the moſt wiſe, godly, grave women are habited.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99599:18"/>
               <p n="2">2 That they be without wantonneſs, waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs or curious nicer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, or new fangled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for faſhion. God viſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth for <hi>ſtrange apparel, Zeph.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Without pride, Vanity or Exceſs, or thinking better of themſelves for them.</p>
               <p n="4">4 So that they place their chiefeſt fineneſs in their inward adornings rather then out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, more in their <hi>Graces and good works</hi> then in their <hi>Garments;</hi> and indeavour by the outward ornament of their bodies to ſet forth the inward beauty of their ſoules.</p>
               <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">2 Of behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. Tit: 2, 3.</note> Alſo modeſty of behaviour, to expreſs the inward holineſs of their hearts in ſober deportment, in countenance, geſture and ſpeech; to <hi>open their mouths with diſcretion, Prov.</hi> 31.26.
<note place="margin">Prov. 7.11, 12 and 9.13.</note> and bridle their tongues, and not be as the harlot babling and clamorous, who is as extravagant in her Tongue as in her feet. Good wives ſhould account meekneſs of ſpirit their chief ornament, and take heed they be not either</p>
               <p n="1">1 Proud, or imperious in their ſpirits, ſpeeches, looks, Carriage:</p>
               <p n="2">2 Or unquiet, turbulent, impatient, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way brawling or chiding. Such wives are neither credit nor comfort to their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, but a continual vexation: Thorns in their ſides, and pricks in their eyes. <hi>The contentions of a wife are a continual dropping,</hi> 19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. and 27.15. Like rain that falls into all the rooms of a houſe, which is very tedious and irkſome.
<note place="margin">Prov. 21.9.25.21.</note> 
                  <hi>It is better to Aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> in the Corner of a houſe-top, then with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rawling woman in a wide houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99599:18"/>
               <p>Thus much concerning the particular du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Husband to wife, and of the wife to her Husband.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2. Duties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to both. 7.</note> 2. Now follow the Duties Common to both husband and wife; and to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by both, or Exerciſed to, or with, or for both, which are equally reciprocal and of like Obligation. Theſe are ſeven.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">1 Prayer.</note> 1. Prayer to God, frequent and fervent, both joyntly and ſeverally, for all mariage Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and mariage Comforts. Eſpecially,</p>
               <p n="1">1. For ſutableneſſe of Diſpoſition; that God would faſhion your hearts alike.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For wiſdom to carry with moſt beauty, amiableneſs and ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tneſs, for the benefit, and advantage, comfort and encouragement one of another.</p>
               <p n="3">3 For Gods preſence with you in it, and for Gods bleſſing upon it, and that God would build you a houſe, (<hi>Pſalm.</hi> 127.) by giving you hopeful children, faithful ſervants, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed goods. Let Husband and wife intereſt God much in their Mariage by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1 Becauſe a Conjugal condition can be no more comfortable or ſatisfactory to us, then God maketh it. It will be an empty thing if God do not fill it, and bitter if God do not ſweeten it. It is not the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of a Husband or a Wife, but of God in them or with them, that giveth content, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ſatisfaction. We ought in all our wayes to acknowledge God, eſpecially in Mariage, which is one of the chief of our wayes, and a great Turn of our lives which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99599:19"/>concerns the future Comfort thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe mercies got with prayer, are got with a bleſſing, and prove the ſweeteſt mercies of all. Prayer ſanctifies Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.3, 4. and makes the acts of it holy in manner, and happy in end.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2 Love, Tit. 2.4.</note> Common duty is Conjugal love which is not proper to the Husband alone, but ſhould be mutual and reciprocal between them both; To this end husband and wife ought to love one another.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Chiefly for the grace of God the one ſeeth in the other: that being unchangeable, their love will be conſtant. When Religion tieth the knot of affection between them, it holds faſt till death. But when they love one another chiefly for other reſpects, as beauty, wealth, or fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when theſe are ſatisfied or fail, love will cool.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Really at their hearts, or in ſincerity. For to diſſemble affections, and Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit love and kindneſs, will deprive them of the comfort and ſweetneſſe of mariage, and make it in Time a burden and bitterneſs to them. Sincere love knits their hearts as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n joynes their hands together; Elſe they will not cleave, but ſit looſe; and be ready to leave one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4. Grounds of mutual love.</note> But there be four ſpecial Grounds of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual love and deareneſs between Husband and wife, <hi>ſcil.</hi> Donation, Propriety, Union and Neceſſity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Donation They are ſpecial gifts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99599:19"/>by God, the one upon the other,
<note place="margin">1 Donation, Prov. 18.22. and 19.14.</note> which ſhould be a precious Endearment of one to other, Thus they ſhould look at them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. This is the woman God hath given to me to be a meet help for me, above al the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the world. So this is that man God hath fited for me and given to me for a head and Guide above all other men in the world.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2 Propriety</note> Propriety, or the Mutual Intereſt they have by matrimony, one in another. They are one anothers <hi>Owne,</hi> properly and peculiarly; ſo as they are no bodies elſe; and ſo as no perſon or thing in the world is their own; for they are maried, One to another; ſo are they to no body, to nothing beſides. The Apoſtle aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts this matrimonial intereſt in the 1. of <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. <hi>Let every man have his own wife; and every woman have her own husband. The wiſe hath not power of her own body but her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band nor the Husband hath power of his owne body but the wife,</hi> ſo as not to account their own bodyes to be at their own diſpoſal, The wife is the Husband, only one, and he is hers.</p>
               <p>They ſhould be <hi>mutual darlings</hi> one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, becauſe they are <hi>mutual Proprietors</hi> one of another: by ſelf reſignation of each to other they give themſelves mutual power one over another. Now every one loveth his own beſt, <hi>non quia pulchrum, ſed quia Suum,</hi> his own Children, his own goods, his own houſe <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for propriety more then for beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; beauſe they are his own. Shall a man love any thing that is his own but his wife? or better then his wife? or ſhall a wife love any thing that is her own but her husband?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99599:20"/>or better then her husband? or ſhall a man love other mens wives, or a woman love other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens husbands better then their own? <hi>Peculia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Intereſt</hi> is a Ground of <hi>Speciality of love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 Union.</note> Ground of ſpecial love between them is union. The Conjunction Husband and wiſe have one with another. They two are in many reſpects as one perſon: and ſo one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as they are not (or ſhould not be) with any one beſides in all the world, to wit <hi>one fleſh, Gen.</hi> 2.24. as it were incarnated one to another: <hi>Adam</hi> acknowledged this, when God had made the woman for him and brought (or maried) her to him, he ſaid, <hi>This is now bone of my bone, and fleſh of my fleſh,</hi> to ſhew his Thankfulnes to God and love to his wife,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.23.</note> as wondering at Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him therein. Mariage is a moral con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of two perſons, ſo as Man and wife are in Law one fleſh by Gods Ordinance. It is the ſtricteſt bond of any relation, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a fellowſhip of the deareſt amitie, nearer then that between Parents and Children. Though children have their fleſh and bone from their Parents, yet they are not one fleſh with their Parents. <hi>Therefore ſhall a man leave his father, and mother and ſhall cleave unto his wiſe,</hi> This,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.24.</note> was the ſanction of mariage. All Society muſt be left, that this between man and wife may be kept. This is <hi>Pauls</hi> rule: <hi>Let not the wiſe depart from her husband,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.0.11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ach. 2, 16.</note> and <hi>Let not the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band put away his wife, for God hates putting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> The wife muſt be an individual compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life. The ſaying of the Philoſopher, that perfect friendſhip is onely between two, is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99599:20"/>moſt true, in this caſe, between man and wife, becauſe they two are by mariage made one.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4 Neceſſity.</note>The 4 Ground of ſpiritual love between them is, Neceſſity of the one for the other, even for their being, as well as for their walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In both theſe reſpects we may underſtand that of the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Neither is the man without the woman; neither, is the woman without the man in the Lord.</hi> The man is not without the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (nor can be) becauſe man now is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and born of a woman. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is not without the man;
<note place="margin">Job. 14.1.</note> becauſe ſhe is now begotten of man, ſo that they are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Cauſes the one of the other. The woman hath her Generation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the man, the man hath his conception and birth from the woman. They cannot be, much leſs be well, the one without the other. The Husband ſhould look at his wife, as <hi>Cauſa ſine qua non,</hi> a help he cannot well be without, for God ſaid, <hi>It is not good that man ſhould be alone;</hi> and the woman ſhould look at her husband, under the ſame notion. It is not good for the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to be alone. Therefore the husband ſhould not inſult over his wife, becauſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority over her, nor the wife be diſcouraged becauſe of her inferiority or ſubjection to him; becauſe they have need the one of the other; as fellowes to bear and draw in one yoke together. Now mutual Neceſſity ſhould breed mutual love between them. What is ſo dear unto the wife as the childe of her Womb? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49 15. yet the husband ſhould be dearer to her, as <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kanah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannah,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.8.</note> Am not I better to thee then ten ſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99599:21"/>
               <p n="3">3
<note place="margin">3 Common du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> is Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> Common duties between Husband and wife is communion (which flowes from the union of their Perſons by mariage, for union is the ground of Communion) or communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of their bodies, ſouls, goods and reſpects.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1 Of bodies.</note> Of their bodies, by <hi>mutual benevolence</hi> performed by the one to the other, 1. <hi>Gor.</hi> 7.3.4.</p>
               <p n="2">2 By <hi>cohabitation</hi> (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7) or dwelling together, unleſs it be for a time, and upon neceſſary Occaſions: 3. <hi>by conjugal fidelity,</hi> reſerving themſelves intirely and peculiarly proper, the one for the other, as Chriſt and his Church doth, <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">2 Of ſouls.</note> Of their ſouls, for the ſpiritual good of both. The heart, as well as the body ſhould be common between Husband and wife. One ſaith, that both the body and the ſoul are united together in Mariage. Conjugal love will make hearts advance together as well as bodies; as amical love doth friends. <hi>The Soul of Jonathan was knit with the Soul of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, and Jonathan loved him, as his own ſoul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.1. as luſtful love makes the ſouls of unclean perſons to cleave together, as well as their bodies, as <hi>Shechems</hi> ſoul clave to <hi>Dinah Jacobs</hi> daughter, whom he defiled, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.3.
<note place="margin">1 Kings 11.3.</note> and <hi>Solomon</hi> clave unto many ſtrange women in love. But I ſhall ſpeak more of this Soul communion between maried per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the fourth common duty.</p>
               <p n="3">3
<note place="margin">3. Of Gods.</note> Of their Goods and Eſtates, labours and indeavours; a joynt fruition thereof for mutual benefit and Comfort.</p>
               <p n="4">4
<note place="margin">4. Of reſpects to their kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</note> Alſo there ſhould be a communion of due reſpect and loving kindneſs, to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99599:21"/>kindred and friends that pertain to either partie. The Husband and Wife lie as <hi>corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones</hi> in the wall, to joyn ſeveral alliances and kindreds together; and ought to carry very reſpectfully to their Affinity contracted by Mariage. <hi>Eſau's</hi> wives offended greatly in grieving the hearts of their Husbands pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.35.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">4. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the ſalvation one of another.</note> Common duty is to further the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſoul good one of another, as given of God, to that end. Husband and Wife ſhould labour to gain one another to Chriſt and help one another to Heaven <hi>What knoweſt thou, O wife,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, but thou mayeſt be a means to ſave thy Husband,</hi> and <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t knoweſt thou, O man, but thou mayest ſave thy wife.</hi> However this ought to be the Serious indeavors of both. If thou know not whether thou ſhalt, yet try whether thou canſt.</p>
               <p>To this end Extend your deſires and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in three particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1 To heal infirmities the one ſeeth in the other, as pride, paſſion, diſcontent, folly, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, exceſs, or the like. Take the fitteſt Time, when the parties may beſt be wrought upon, it is apteſt to take Impreſſions; or is in a tract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ductile frame: and chuſe the beſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to doe it in a taking efficacious way. Beg wiſedom of God for it, rightly to obſerve what is amiſſe in a yoke-fellow, to heal it, or to cover it. Happy is that couple, whom God makes Heaven, of Spiritual Infirmities (or Spiritual Phyſitians) one to another. The wife ſhould be <hi>a ſecond Conſcience to</hi> her Husband, <hi>a boſome Monitor,</hi> to tell him privately of his faults, to amend them.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99599:22"/>
               <p n="2">2 To increaſe Graces mutually, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage one another to the Exerciſe of them, as, of faith, love, patience, of prudence, piety, charity, ſobriety and the like.</p>
               <p n="3">3 To Excite and Encourage unto duties, and to provoke one another unto good works, and to quicken and ſharpen, or edge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thereunto, to take off dulneſs and averſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the one from the other. <hi>Yoke fellows</hi> ſhould draw on one another, to God and good, and towards Heaven, to publick ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and private exerciſes, and to the Communion of Saints. They ſhould be <hi>goads and ſpurs</hi> each to other, and worſhip God together as Companions in his ſervice; and <hi>fellow travellers</hi> walking hand in hand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the kingdom of glory. That they may be like <hi>Zacharias and Elizabeth, both righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, walking in all the Commandments and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Lord blameleſs, Luc.</hi> 1.6. <hi>like Abraham and Sara</hi> both believers: like <hi>Elka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah and Hannah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.</note> both true worſhipers of God, like <hi>Aquila and Priſcilla,</hi> both helpers in the work of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.3, 4. Now, if either father or mother believe the children are holy federally, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. and many promiſes are made to them, eſpecially if both the Parents be ſaints and believers, God bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch with pious and proſperous children, which are double bleſſings, as he did <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> with an <hi>Iſaac; Elkanah</hi> and <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> with a <hi>Samuel, Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> with a <hi>John; Manoah</hi> and his wife with a <hi>Sampſon.</hi> Such Godly compeers make mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it ſelf honourable; and they will live and die with Glory.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99599:22"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">5 Patience.</note>The fifth Common duty is Patience, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Wife ſhould not onely labour to heal (of which before) but (if they cannot) yet to bear with infirmities, one in another. Remember this Rule, never to be angry both at once, but the one ſhould bear with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers frowardneſs and Paſſion; and for a time give way to it. This is the way, to overcome and quench paſſion in a yoke-fellow, and to make them afterwards love one another bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when the one by yeelding a little hath conquered the other; whereas to be both angry at once, is to add fewel to the fire, and to make the ſlame of Contention between them very great, this will diſſolve the glue of affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that made them cleave together, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them, and make of one, two. Patience is neceſſary to prevent breaches and preſerve Conjugal Amity and familiarity between ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Couples; and to poſſeſs themſelves and one another. It was the ſpeech of a godly man, I count it a neceſſary Qualification in one whom I may match my ſelf unto, to have no predominant humor in her, which I cannot bear; but to be able to bear any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity of mine. Another Reverend man (as is reported) ſeeing a very cholerick couple live very lovingly and quietly together as Husband and wife; asked them how they could ſo ſweetly agree and conſort together: to whom the man anſwered, when my wifes fit is upon her, I yeeld to her, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did to <hi>Sarah;</hi> and when my fit is upon me ſhe yeelds to me, and ſo we never ſtrive together,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99599:23"/>but aſſunder. This mutual forbearance each of other will beget contention with their Coujugal Condition; and further their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to ſute their minde to their Choice, and to be well pleaſed one in another after Mariage,
<note place="margin">Mal. 15.</note> though before mariage they might have fitted their Choice to their minde. That Mariage hath a great bleſſing in it, wherein the greateſt Contention between Man and Wife, is who ſhould love each other moſt, and pleaſe one another beſt.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">6. Procreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Children.</note> 6. The ſixth Common duty, Procreation of children, <hi>I will,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul that the younger women mary and bear children.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.14. eſpecially to ſeek <hi>a godly ſeed.</hi> To this end Husband and wife ſhould wreſt by prayer with God, not onely to bleſs them with the fruit of the womb, but with ſuch a ſeed as ſhall be bleſſed, is not onely to give them chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but children of promiſe as well as of providence; ſuch as he will make his children by grace, as well as their children by nature, heirs of God and coheirs with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>God at the firſt made onely <hi>one woman</hi> for <hi>one man,</hi> though he being the God of the ſpirit of all fleſh, had power to have made more: but he did Conjoyn one woman onely to that one man (and ſtill continueth his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, of the ſame ſingle Copulation) <hi>that he might ſeek a ſeed of God:</hi> that is, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and holy poſterity, ſuch as might worſhip him, the onely true God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate his Church. This is a proper and principal end of Mariage, to wit the procrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of children, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the propagation of Gods
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99599:23"/>worſhip and of his Church (of which I ſhall ſpeak again afterwards) yea this was the end of it, Even in mans Innocency; when he was without ſin. Hence amongſt Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>virginity was a grief,</hi> as in the Caſe of <hi>Jephtahs</hi> daughter, <hi>Judg</hi> 11.37, 40. and <hi>barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was accounted a ſhame and reproach,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 5.6, 7.</note> as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeths</hi> ſpeech implies, <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.25. <hi>Hannah</hi> had experience hereof, upon this Account, becauſe they could not increaſe the Church of God. For which end, <hi>Paul</hi> bids the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger women mary.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tim. 2 14.</note> Whereas an ungodly ſeed ſerves to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the Synagogue of Satan, Idolatry and profaneneſs: and cauſe exceeding grief and troubles to their godly Parents.</p>
               <p>And as it ſhould be their earneſt deſire to bring forth a godly ſeed; ſo ſhould it be their care to bring th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m up for God, in the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and nurture of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Epheſ 6.7.</note> in the fear and knowledge of God, and in his worſhip, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their ſouls better then their bodies. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> praiſed his mother, that ſhe travelled in greater pain for his Soul, then ſhe did in bringing forth his bodie. <hi>Solomons</hi> Mother taught him <hi>a Propheſie,</hi> that is, leſſons of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, and temperance, and the properties of a good wife, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. His father <hi>David</hi> compoſed a Pſalm for his inſtruction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. <hi>Timotheus</hi> mother taught him the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from his Infancy, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5 3.15.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">7 to build a godly family</note> 7. Common dutie is to build a godly family; not onely by the procreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and religious Education of children (which is a pillar of the houſe) but by a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99599:24"/>wiſe and godly Goverment and ordering of the houſe, in which the wife ought to act her part. <hi>I will,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, that the younger women mary, and bear children,</hi> and <hi>guide the houſe</hi> (that is domeſtick affairs).
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>1 Tim. 5.14. <hi>domi-portae.</hi>
                  </note> To this end they ought to be <hi>diſcreet,</hi> that is prudent and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, <hi>and keepers at home, Titus</hi> 2.5. houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives, to carry their houſes (as it were) on their backs, as ſnails do. The Harlot doth not ſo.
<note place="margin">Prov. 7.11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Her feet abide not in her houſe, now ſhe is without, now in the ſtreet.</hi> But Abraham, when he was askt, <hi>where is Sarah thy wife?</hi> he ſaid,
<note place="margin">Gen. 18, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>behold ſhe is in the Tent.</hi> To this end Husband and wife ſhould put forth joynt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours in five particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                     <p>5 Things are requiſite hereto.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Family du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                     <p>Jer. 10.25.</p>
                  </note> To performe holy duties in their houſes conſtantly, of reading the Scriptures and of prayer, <hi>Evening and Morning.</hi> For without pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, they and their Familie lies open to Gods wrath and judgments. Let them pray with their family in the morning, becauſe ſome of them may fall ſick, and die before night; and pray in the Evening alſo, to commit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their houſe to Gods ſafe keeping from all peril and danger, for they know not what a Night may bring forth, or day either, and if evils befal them, their hearts will ſmite them for neglect of this neceſſary duty of prayer in their families. Alſo to Catechize repeat ſermons, and teach all in their houſe their duties, and to ſeek the ſouls good of their ſervants as well as of their children, and as well as to expect the ſervice of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and to charge them all to walk in Gods ways, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did his children and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99599:24"/>after him. <hi>Gen</hi> 18.19.
<note place="margin">Prov. 4.1. to 5. 1. Chron. 28.9.</note> and as <hi>David</hi> charged his ſon <hi>Solomon</hi> in his life, and at his death 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.1.2. This is the mothers du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alſo, to teach and command her children their duties. <hi>My ſon,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomen,
<note place="margin">Prov. 1.8. and 6.20.</note> keep thy fathers Commandment, and forſake not the Law of thy mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 24.15.</note>The maſter of the houſe ſhould reſolve with <hi>Joſhua, I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord,</hi> every day together (what ever other familes do) we will pray and read Gods word, that is, perform holy duties together, for the Glory of God and the good of all our ſouls, as well as eat, drink talk and ſleep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and with <hi>David,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 101.2.</note> I will walk in the mideſt of my houſe with a perfect heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eſther 4.16.</note>The wife alſo ſhould be a help to her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in family duties, and no hinderance therein. Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> and her Maides will faſt and pray: For if the wife ſhould draw back from holy duties and be a diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him therein, the ſoul of her husband (if he be godly) can take no pleaſure in her. She is in a poſture tending to perdition, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.38.39.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mr. Abbot.</note>I have read a ſad ſtory reported by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Miniſter upon his own knewledge, of an honeſt Chriſtian that had a wife, world ly and diſtruſtful: and he being much in Godly Excerciſe, Morning and Evening in his family, She would diſturb him, and goe about ratling her keyes, or making ſome other noiſe, to hinder him, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that his Time ſpent that way, might be imployed, in getting of mony for his family.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99599:25"/>This woman was given over by God to the Devils Temptations ſo far, that ſhe thruſt a knife into the pit of her ſtomack, and killed her ſelf, yet before ſhe died, ſhe confeſſed thus much to that Miniſter, and craved Gods pardon as well as ſhe could. Had it not been better, that ſhe had borne her husband company in holy duties, and ſo gone hand in hand to heaven together?</p>
               <p>Further ſet up Gods word to be the Law of your houſe, to order your family and all the affaires of it according to the Rule of it. For Gods word moulds and ſhapes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very perſon in it for his Imployment, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects and keeps them in their ſeveral rankes, Places, and duties. This is the way to have <hi>a Church in your houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16.5.</note> as <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> had.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2 Chuſe good ſervants.</note> To chuſe good ſervants: ſuch as know and fear God, or as appear tractable and hopeful to be inſtructed, and wrought upon. Set <hi>David</hi> before you as a pattern herein, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.6, 7. Suffer no diſordered ſwearing rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons to come into your houſe or to tarry in your ſight, ſuch as will bring ſin and a curſe along with them. Covet earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly to have a choyce pickt family,
<note place="margin">Acts 10.2</note> ſuch as <hi>Cornelius</hi> had, who <hi>feared God and all his houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 Exclude ſin.</note> To ſhut ſin out of doores, as exceſſive drinking, gaming, ſwearing, lying, pride, contentions,
<note place="margin">Job 11.14. ch. 22.23.</note> vanities.</p>
               <p>Follow the Councel which <hi>Jobs</hi> friends gave him, as <hi>Zophar, Let not wickedneſſe dwel in your Tabernacle,</hi> and <hi>Eliphaz, Put iniquity
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99599:25"/>far from your Tabernacle, then you ſhall know that your Tabernacle ſhall be in peace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.24.</note> God will keep houſe for you, when you are from home, as <hi>Bildad,
<note place="margin">Job. 8.6.</note> If you be pure and upright God will make the Habitation of your righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs proſperous.</hi> Let it be your care to make it righteous; and God will make it proſperous.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Look well to the wayes of your houſhold,
<note place="margin">4 Overſee the family.</note> to prevent or ſupreſs ſin and to ſtop the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings thereof, to cheriſh &amp; incourage good in all that live with you, to reduce thoſe that go aſtray in opinion or in converſation. This is the duty of the wife as well as of the Husband.
<note place="margin">Prov. 31.27. 1 Sam. 3.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>The vertuous woman looketh well to the wayes of her houſhold;</hi> Becauſe <hi>Elies ſonnes made themſelves vile, and he reſtrained them not, God judged his houſe for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <note place="margin">5. To Sanctify the ſabbath.</note> To keep holy the Sabbath day, not onely you, but all within your houſe? the charge whereof lyeth mainly on the maſter of the houſe, and next upon the miſtreſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.9, 10.</p>
               <p>This Godly Covenant of your houſhold will draw down Gods protection, and bleſſing upon your habitation, relations, and upon all your affairs.</p>
               <p>The uſe hereof is to exhort all Marying and married perſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1 To learn theſe mariage duties, both ſpecial and Common.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Learn theſe mariage duties.</note> For any to mary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they know their dutie, or how to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry therein, is like ſetting up, before one hath learnt the trade: or like anſwering a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, before one hears it, which is folly and ſhame unto him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.13.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99599:26"/>
               <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them.</note> To perform theſe duties of mariage car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>full, and conſtantly, I commend unto you four Motives or inducements hereunto.
<note place="margin">4 Motives.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1 Duties of Mariage a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e matters of Religion.</note> Though Mariage in it ſelf be but a civil matter, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the duties of Mariage are Matters of Religion, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſcience and obedience to the goſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing fully preſcribed and injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> And Chriſt will one day come in ſlaming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire to ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vengeance on them that ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not the Goſpel, in the precepts of it. 2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">2 To do the dutie. This to get the Comfort thereof.</note> In the diligent and Conſcionable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the dutie of mariage, you may expect the comforts, benefits and bleſſings of mariage. A wife may draw forth the love and kindeneſs of a husband, and a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band may extract the helpfulneſs and comfort of a wife, by the religious doing of their duties the one to the other. For man or woman to expect the Comfort of a Relation, and to neglect the duty thereof, is to tempt God;
<note place="margin">Math. 25.24.</note> and to act the part of a hard man, who looks to reap where he hath not ſowen, and to gather where he hath not ſtrowed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 The mariage covenant.</note> Motive. The ſolemn league and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant you enter into mutually at Mariage (whereof <hi>God himſelf is a witneſs, Malac.</hi> 2.14. both of your making it, and your breaking it or keeping it; Hence it is called the <hi>Covenant of God;</hi> this ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and obligeth you ſtrongely to all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial duties.
<note place="margin">Prov. 2.17.</note> Covenant breakers (even in wedlock) God will judge.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">4 This will be a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</note> The good Carriage of Husband and wife each to other, according to the Goſpel,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99599:26"/>will be a good example or patern to all other Relations in the family, to ſet them a copy; or teach them how to carry therein, and to put them in order. Without this all would be out of frame; the children unruly, and diſobedient, and the ſervants unfaithful and diſorderly.</p>
               <p>So much of the Duties of Mariage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now followes the third thing conſiderable in mariage.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99599:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The Benefits of Mariage.</head>
               <p>WHich may be referred to five heads. They are 1. Perſonal 2. Domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal 3. Political 4. Eccleſiaſtical 5. Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1 Perſonal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits.</note> The Perſonal Benefits of Mariage ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the parties themſelves are 4. to wit,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Society 2. Sanctity 3. Copartnerſhip 4. furtherance of the myſtical Mariage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and the ſoul.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1 Society.</note> Society. God made man <hi>a ſociable Creature,</hi> in reſpect both of the Conſtitution of his body, and diſpoſition of his minde: and ſaid,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>It is not good for man to be alone.</hi> Though God made <hi>Adam</hi> lord over all the Creatures, and brought them to him, to give names to them all, as a ſign of his ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty and authority over them; yet for all this man was alone; for among all the creatures there was not found a help meet for him or like to him in Nature: a fit and ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Companion, that ſhould be <hi>alter ego, a ſecond ſelf</hi> to him. God ſet all the creatures before him, ere he gave him a wife; that (as ſome think) he ſeeing their ſexes, might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have a help in his kind and nature alſo.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99599:27"/>God ſaw it was not good for the irrational living creatures to be alone,
<note place="margin">Gen. 7.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> therefore he crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them <hi>male and female,</hi> in Heb. cal'd the man and his wife, for the increaſe of their kind (to this end God bid <hi>Noah</hi> take into the Arke two of every ſort of living things to keep them alive, <hi>they ſhall be male and female, Gen.</hi> 6.19, 20. and God created them male and female together, but he did not ſo in mankind for <hi>Adam</hi> was firſt formed, then <hi>Eve.</hi> Though it be ſaid in <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27. that God created them that is <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi>) male and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, yet not together. This is an anticipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The 27, 28. <hi>verſes</hi> of <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> are to be made up with the 17, 18, 19. <hi>verſes</hi> of the 2. <hi>chapter</hi> together into one Relation. This was the Cauſe of the Creation of the woman, becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> was alone (God ſaw <hi>Adam</hi> Solitary and defective till he had a wife. I will make him, ſaith God, a help commodious for him. God created the woman <hi>by delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Councel,</hi> as before he had done the man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26, 27. <hi>Let us make man in our Image.</hi> The creation of the woman was the work of the Trinity as well as of the man. When <hi>Adam</hi> ſaw no other fit help for him, among all the Creatures, it might make him the more prize a wife: and count it better to <hi>loſe a rib</hi> then to <hi>lack a wife;</hi> to want part of himſelf, then not to have a ſecond ſelf. A wiſe was the <hi>Complement</hi> of all to <hi>Adam:</hi> and <hi>a Recovery of</hi> his loſt Rib. If <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, when he was perfect in body and ſoul, and when the whole world was his own, ſtood in need of a wife even for ſociety, to be his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99599:28"/>Companion, and it was not good for him that was ſo happy to be alone, much leſs for poor ſinful, ſickly miſerable man ſince the fall, what need hath he of a wife, even for Society?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.9, 10.</note>
                  <hi>Two are better then one,</hi> ſaith the Preacher, that is fully verified in conjugal Society, though this onely is not meant here, but that ſociety in all ſorts of affaires is better than Solitarineſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">Sanctity. 2</note> The Second Benefit of mariage is ſanctity, to prevent ſin, and keep us pure from Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of fleſh and ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.2.</note> From outward acts of uncleanneſs. To <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void fornication let every man have his owne wife</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>and every woman her own husband.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 From inward Luſts,
<note place="margin">Ver. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>It is better to mary then to burn.</hi> Mariage is a meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent burning in luſt.</p>
               <p>Mariage is a preſervation of chaſtity, and prvention of heart adultery which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our makes to be <hi>to look on a woman and luſt after her.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.28.</note> Though mariage was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before there was ſin, and <hi>Adam</hi> needed it not as a Remedie againſt Incontinency but upon another account. But ſince the fall it is of neceſſary and ſoveraign uſe, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſin, and to procure or promote our ſanctincation, that we may poſſeſs our veſſels in holines and Honour, not in the loſt of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence:
<note place="margin">Theſ. 4.3.4, 5.</note> This is the will of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 Copartner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> Benefit is Copartnerſhip in all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons better and worſe: As yoke fellows to take part and ſhare equally together there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99599:28"/>
               <p n="1">1. To be a ſolace and comfort one to other in adverſity, as in ſickneſs, poverty, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. What a great comfort is a loving ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der husband to his dear wife in her ſickneſs? and ſhe the like to him in his.
<note place="margin">Prov. 17.17,</note> As <hi>a brother is born for adverſity:</hi> ſo many couples finde cauſe to ſay, that they were maried together for a time of adverſity: and that God brought them together to be mutual helps, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts at ſuch a time as this;
<note place="margin">Judg. 13.22, 23.</note> as he did <hi>Eſther</hi> to the kingdom, <hi>Eſther.</hi> 4.14. how did <hi>Mancahs</hi> wife comfort him, when he was plunged deep into fear of death?</p>
               <p n="2">2. To be companions in joy; the delight one of another in proſperity; <hi>the deſire of the eyes, as Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kiels</hi> wife was,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 24.16. Eccleſ. 9.9.</note> and the joy of the heart; to live joyfully and comfortably to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah,
<note place="margin">Gen. 26.8.</note> Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebekah</hi> did. <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>melech</hi> looking out through a window, ſaw <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſporting (or laughing and rejoycing) with his wife. Which implies ſome pleaſing familiarity, or ſign of love and delight between them: Husband and wife are glaſſes to look one anothers face in: and echoes of delight, refreſhments and reflections or repercuſſions of pleaſure and joy the one to the other; and mutual chearings each of other.</p>
               <p n="4">4
<note place="margin">4 Furtherance of the Myſtical Mariage.</note> Benefit of Mariage is, the Furtherance of the Myſtical Mariage between Chriſt and the Soul. Both Husband and wife ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their conjugal Relation and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip together to promote the Communion of their ſouls with Chriſt, as the Spiritual hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99599:29"/>thereof. To this end we ſhould do three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1. To look at Chriſt as our Huſband. Hoſeah. 2.19 20.</note> To look at <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt our Maker and Redeemer as our Husband (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.5) as maried to us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. and at our ſelves as betrothed to him, in righteouſneſs and loving kindneſs, mercy and faithfulneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">2 To expect the love of a Husband from him.</note> To expect all that love, kindneſs, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, Comfort, nouriſhings and cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from Chriſt ſpiritually (<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29.) which the wife looks to receive from her Husband corporally. As the ſpouſe doth in the <hi>Canticles: the kiſſes of his mouth, Cant.</hi> 1.2. the Embraces of his arms, <hi>cap.</hi> 2.6. the refreſhments of his preſence, <hi>to ſit under his ſhadow with great delights.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 2, 3.</note> Cordials and Refo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillations to ſupport and comfort the Soul in his abſence: this is to be <hi>ſtaid with flagons, and comforted with apples, verſe</hi> 5. Alſo the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Chriſt to the ſoul, for he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>I will manifeſt my ſelf to you, John</hi> 14.21. Will not the husband let his wife behold his face? and the ſence of his love ſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the heart, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Oh that is better then wine, Cant.</hi> 1.2. The Communication of the ſeed of Grace, this is the benevolence which Chriſt as a Husband renders to our ſouls,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.3.</note> to make them fruitful in good works. <hi>We are maried unto Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that we ſhould bring forth fruit unto God;</hi> Hence the ſpouſe ſaith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.4. Cant. 1.16. Col. 1.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Our bed is green.</hi> This denotes the fruitfulneſs and flouriſhing of the ſoul in every good work, by the ſpiritual Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or heavenly Conjunction of Chriſt with the ſoul.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99599:29"/>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3. To perform our duty to him.</note> To expreſs and perform all that duty ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually to Chriſt, which the wife doth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally to her husband, as ſubjection, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence love, loyalty, chaſtity, ſerviceableneſs. To reſerve our hearts wholly, ſolely, intirely for him (as his bed to lie in, his Throne to rule in; now the husbands bed and the Kings throne admit no Corrivals) <hi>to be for him and not for another</hi> (<hi>Hoſea,</hi> 3.3.) <hi>to tarry many dayes</hi> for his gracious Return and manifeſtation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to our ſouls, after his departures and Occultations of himſelf (in our apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) from us: to embrace and imboſom Chriſt, and <hi>lay him between our breasts,
<note place="margin">Micah. 7 19, Cant. 1 13.</note> as a bundle of mirrhe,</hi> or perfumed bags. To ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject our deſires to him, and ſubmit our wills to his, that his will may be ours, and there may be but one will between Chriſt and our ſoules: to refer our ſelves wholly to be at his command and diſpoſe. To open our hearts unto him, inviting and intreating him earneſtly to come in, and not onely to ſup and lodge in them, but to make his abode in and with our ſouls. <hi>I opened to my beloved,</hi> ſaith the ſpouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.5. <hi>To be ſick of love for Chriſt,</hi> as the ſpouſe was, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.8. ſick with grief for his abſence, and with deſires of his preſence, and to ſeek him up and down, as the ſpouſe did, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. by night on our bed (in private inquiries, breathings and reſtleſs deſires and purſuits after him) and in the ſtreetes and broad wayes of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and communion of ſaints, and not to give over till we find him, and having found him to hold him faſt and not let him go
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99599:30"/>to joyn ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſelves, 1. Chriſt, by faith and love to be one ſpirit with him (<hi>he that is joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Lord is one ſpirit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6, 17, as Husband and wife are one fleſh.</p>
               <p>To leave father and mother, yea wife and children, houſe, goods, land, all we have, whatſoever is near or dear to us for Chriſts ſake, to follow Chriſt, and to go to Chriſt, which is beſt of all for us.
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Law of the Churches mariage with Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Hearken O daughter, forget thine owne people and thy fathers houſe. He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth father or mother, ſon, or daughter</hi> &amp;c. <hi>more then me, ſaith Christ, is not worthy of me, Math,</hi> 10.37. to have me to be the Husband of his ſoul.
<note place="margin">Luk. 14.26.</note> Chriſt requires we ſhould leave all to cleave to him.</p>
               <p>The Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtle in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. deſcribes the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and amity of Chriſt and the ſpouſe by the ſameneſs of fleſh, which Mariage cauſeth between Husband and wife: and reacheth maried perſons their duties, by the communion of Chriſt and the Church: and the ſouls duty to Chriſt by the wives duty to her Husband. This is to <hi>ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize mariage;</hi> and to improve it to a high, holy and heavenly uſe, the benefit whereof w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l extend to the days of Eternity.</p>
               <p>What Expreſſion of Conjugal, love is there between man and wife, which ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth not a reſemblance of ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual intercourſe between Chriſt and the ſoul?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Benefit of mariage is Domeſtical, the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99599:30"/>building of families and kindreds,
<note place="margin">2 Domeſtical Benefits of Mariage. Ruth, 4.11.</note> and the multiplication of them. Women are Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hereof as well as men; <hi>Rachel and Leah did build the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> Indeed mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is the fountain of all humane ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Benefit is Political.
<note place="margin">3 Political.</note> Mariage laies the foundation of cities, countreys, nations: of Lawes and civil goverment: of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths and Kingdoms: all theſe are ſuperſtructures upon Mariage. alſo it furniſheth the ſame, with uſeful and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable inſtruments. That Mariage up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds the fabrick of the republick; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation and ſucceſſion thereof. Hence it is cald the <hi>Seminary of the Common wealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">4 Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</note> Benefit of Mariage is Eccleſiaſtical: the Propagation of the Church of God, and of the tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e religion, to repleniſh it with mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as it furniſhed Chriſt the head of it and Saviour of the world with a body on earth, (for he was conceived and born of a woman, that was begotten in wedlock.)</p>
               <p>Mariage afforded fleſh unto the Meſſiah, and provides materials for Gods Church, both ſtones and pillars, and helps to fill heaven with heirs, therefore Mariage is called the <hi>Seed plot and Nurſery of the church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Benefit of Mariage is univerſal,
<note place="margin">5 Univerſal.</note> the preſervation and increaſe of mankind, this was the end of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ves</hi> creation and Mariage before the fall; and this was Gods benediction upon them. <hi>Be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and multiply and repleniſh the earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1.28.</note> Were it not for mariage; the world would come
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:99599:31"/>to an end. Hence mariage is called, <hi>the pillar of the world under God; the right hand of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1 Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes to God</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. This ſhould teach us thankfulneſs to God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For providing ſo comfortable, uſeful and beneficial a Relation or condition for us, as mariage is. It is <hi>a great bundle of Benefits;</hi> How many both private and publick are bound up together in it as in one volume?</p>
               <p n="2">2. For all the benefit, help and comfort God hath given us particularly in our Mariage, in and by our yoake fellowes. What ſhall I render to the Lord, may the Husband ſay, for giving me ſuch a meet and ſutable help, as I think there is <hi>None ſuch</hi> for me: may the wife ſay, for giving me ſo great a bleſſing in a wiſe, loving, tender Husband; may both Husband and wife ſay, for bleſſing us with the fruit of the wombe, and giving us hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tractable children.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2. This ſhould teach us to improve Mariage for all thoſe ends, for which God appointed it, as</p>
               <p n="1">1. For Gods glory as well as for our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For our ſelves; the good of our ſouls as of our bodies; in ſpirituals as well as in temporals: and for Heaven as well as for earth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For others, not onely to build families, but godly families, ſuch as may know, fear &amp; ſerve God: and may breed and ſend forth uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful perſons (children or ſervants) ſuch as may do ſervice in Church or common wealth, or
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99599:31"/>up religious families abroad. This is an honour and comfort to a maried couple, that out of their houſe as a ſtock or root, many godly families have ſprung and grown, as ſwarms out of a hive, when it is full: that their children being diſpoſed of in theworld, have built ſome; and their ſervants, being maried from them have built other families; and all fearing and worſhipping God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 3. reprovs them that mary for low ends.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 3. Reproves them that mary for poor low ends, as onely or chiefly,</p>
               <p n="1">1. For Carnal ends to ſatisfie the luſts and deſires of the fleſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Or for worldly ends, to get wealth or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, to heighten, greaten, or raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſome way in the world thereby. Such mary the <hi>portion</hi> or Eſtate, rather then the <hi>Perſon</hi> (whether it be man or woman) and may come to have ſorrow enough therewith; and to buy gold too dear. By Gods juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch perſons enjoy few of the benefits of Mariage.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Little ſociety together; when they have obtained their ends, and ſatisfied their luſts, they care little, one for another; and are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to part bed, if not houſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Leſs ſanctity thereby. For their eyes are as full of adultery, and their hearts of unclean affections or luſtings after others men or women, as if they were not maried.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No advantage at all doe they got to their Souls by their mariage, or ſpiritual be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, no help heaven-ward, but rather a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They deſire children, but do not think
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99599:32"/>or care whether they be Godly or no; and they prove many times accordingly.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They build up families, but without a dram of religion or piety in them, ſcarce Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility or common honeſty.</p>
               <p n="6">6. They ſeek great things in the world for their children, but do not indeavour, intend or deſire, they ſhould be uſeful Inſtruments in Church or Comonwealth and they often ſpend prodigally, what their parents got painfully.</p>
               <p n="7">7. They take little or no delight one in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and have little comfort togethes: it may be much grief: being thorns in the ſides and pricks in the eyes, and provocations, the one to the other.</p>
               <p n="8">8. As for the myſtical mariage between Chriſt and Soul, they know not what it means: it is a <hi>paradox</hi> to them, as Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was to Nicodemus.</p>
               <p>How many Husbands and wives have no more benefit by mariage, then the Pagans that knew not God, yea then the beaſts have, to ſatisfie their luſts, which God created male and female as well as them.</p>
               <p>Now I come to the fourth thing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in mariage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99599:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> The Troubles of Mariage.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4 The trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</note>MAriage hath it's croſſes as well as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts: and ſorrowes as well as joyes. It is not all honey, but hath ſome gall and wormwood intermingled. Mariage is but a Bitter-ſweet.</p>
               <p>Many are the cares, fears, ſorrowes, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that attend mariage, even the comforts of it, as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The having of children. Many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows accompany the wife conception, breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, bearing and feeding of them; and many cares and troubles ariſe both to Husband and wite in the education and diſpoſal of them: and if their children prove not well, what a heart break is that to them? beſides, the death of children cauſeth great grief unto parents.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The building of a family; the ordering and governing of it, and making proviſion for the whole houſe.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5 8.</note> He is worſe then an infidel that doth not ſo, ſaith <hi>Paul.</hi> Many incumbrances accompany houſhold affairs. <hi>Martha</hi> had experience thereof. <hi>Luk</hi> 10.40, 41</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99599:33"/>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The care incumbent upon both, how to pleaſe one another, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.33, 34. The word ſignifieth a care joyned with anxiety of mind, the word implies a dividing of the mind (as one ſaith) into diverſe thoughts, caſting this way, and that way, and every way, how to give beſt content.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There may be ſeveral events and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergencies, that prove occaſions of Trouble and grief to them both, as, Loſſes and Croſſes in their Callings, eſtates and affairs; ſickneſſes upon both or either of them; and death at laſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Eſpecially when they are unequally yoked, in Religion or otherwiſe, and they draw diverſe or adverſe ways; the one for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and the other backward: or the one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the other downward. Or when they are unſutably diſpoſed, and their ſpirits are croſs-grain'd, each to other; the one high the other low.</p>
               <p>How many diſcontents and differences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from hence?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The reaſon of it.</note>The reaſon why Mariage hath its croſſes and troubles, is, becauſe it is a thing under the ſun, therefore it is ſubject to vanity and vexation of Spirit, as all other things. The Preacher affirms the ſame from his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Beſides, Mariage is but for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time. When we get above the ſun, and come to be happy in Heaven, we ſhall ſtand in no need of mariage, or of any of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits or comforts of it, which we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy here below,
<note place="margin">Math. 22.30.</note> but we ſhall be as the Angels of God in Heaven.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99599:33"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1 Expect not too much from it.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. Then do not greaten your expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions too much, nor look for more from it then is in it, or can be had from it; as if it was all joy and no ſorrow; all ſweetneſs and no bitterneſs in it, all honey, and no ſting of trouble. To look for more comfort and delight in it, then you can finde; and to finde (or meet with) more trouble and ſorrow in it then you did look for or imagin, will great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſappoint your expectation; and that will beget, not onely diſſatisfaction; and diſcontent, but vexation of ſpirit in you.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2 prepare for troubles.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2. I counſel and exhort all maried per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to expect and prepare for Troubles, and Trials, yea for now ones, and it may be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then ever ye experienced before.</p>
               <p>Mariage croſſes are new things, to thoſe that have lived ſingle and ſolitary lives; you ſtand in need to beg of God wiſdom and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, to bear them and improve them. Paul was a true Prophet herein. <hi>Such</hi> as mary, <hi>ſhall have trouble in the fleſh</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.28.</p>
               <p>Husband and wife have cauſe to expect variety and viciſſitude of turns and changes (from better to worſe, from joy to ſorrow, from pleaſure to pain) in wedlock as well as in any other condition under the ſun: and the time, or ſeveral ſeaſons thereof are deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the appointment and limitation of Gods purpoſe and providence. This is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be the Preachers ſence and Scope, in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1. to 9.
<note place="margin">Eccleſiansj. 1 to 9.</note> wherein he declares the Univerſal uncertainty of future events, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their total dependance upon Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determining purpoſe and overruling provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99599:34"/>which man cannot by all his ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, anxious care or thoughts, poſſibly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent or eſcape. Job had large experience hereof He injoyed the comforts of Subſtance and health, of wife and of many children (ſeven ſons and three daughters which were accounted as his greateſt mercies or bleſſings next to his graces, as his uprightneſs and fear of God, and eſchewing of evil:
<note place="margin">Job1, 2.</note> though ſome reckon their children but as Troubles,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1, 2.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd bils of charges) and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dayes, but afterwards his eſtate was all ſnatcht from him by violent hands, his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were all taken away by a ſudden blow or blaſt, as you may read <hi>Job.</hi> 1.19, 20. and his body was ſmitten with ſore boils from head to fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t chap. 2.7. Then his wife ſaid unto him <hi>Dost thou ſtil retain thine integrity? Curſe God and die</hi> She that ſhould have been a help and comfort to him,
<note place="margin">ver 9.</note> proved a great croſs and trial to him in his affliction, as appears by his ſharp reproof of her.
<note place="margin">verſ. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſpeakeſt as one of the fooliſh women ſpeaketh. What? ſhall we receive good at the hand of God and ſhall we not receive evil?</hi> Even thoſe that are maried muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect (in their conjugal condition) to receive ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l at the hand of God as well as good; loſs of children as well as of goods, and diſeaſes of body, and croſſes in yoak-fellows, and in friends alſo, which were an addition to <hi>Jobs</hi> afflictions, <hi>Job.</hi> 16 2 They proved <hi>miſerable comforters</hi> to him, <hi>Phyſitians of no value,</hi> cha. 13.4 Some think that Satan by his commiſsion mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht have taken away his wife as well as his children, <hi>Job</hi> 1.12. but he kept her alive
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99599:34"/>to be a vexation unto <hi>Job.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mariage at firſt is a ſoft gentle pleaſant thing but, it proves to many afterwards hard, heavy, and uneaſy (through conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant Troubles) more bone then fleſh, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if they want patience, which makes hard things ſoft, and heavy thing; light. Husband and wife that live comfortably and joyfully together for ſometime, may afterwards m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et with new afflictions and Additions to their afflictions, ſuch as they never looked for, nor imagined. Now that ye are forewarn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them, be ye forewarned againſt them, not to bear them out by the head and ſhoulders (as we ſay) in a ſelf hardning, Stoical ſtupid way; but as becometh Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, by the exerciſe of faith and patience, meekneſs and holyneſs in them, and of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to make a ſpiritual uſe and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vement thereof, that ye may gloryfie God in the fire of Wedlock afflictions; and that when God hath tryed you therein you may come forth as Gold (<hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b</hi> 23.10.) leaving the droſs both of your perſonal Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uptions and Conjugal miſcarriages behinde you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. <hi>Socrates</hi> once ſaid to ſome that hit him in the teeth with his wives frowardneſs, that he did thereby learn even within his own doors to be conſtant &amp; patient every where <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> from it.</note>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. The Conſideration of mariage troubles may wean you from it, even at your entrance into it, and prevent your ſurſeition Mariage comforts &amp; delights afterwards. Doth not <hi>Paul</hi> preſcribe and preſſe this upon you? <hi>Let them that have wives be as if they had none</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99599:35"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. and let them that have husbands be as if they had none; for this Rule is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to them both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How may thoſe that have wives be as if they had none? or thoſe that are maried be as if they were not maried?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Five wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1. Let not Mariage be a hinderance to ſerving God or ſaving our ſoules.</note> Firſt by not ſuffering out mariage to be an Impediment or Diſcouragment to us either,
<list>
                     <item>1. In ſerving of God.</item>
                     <item>2. Or in working out the Salvation of our ſouls.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>When we will wait upon God in his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ordinances and ſeek God in private duties, both in our families and cloſets, and meet God in the communion of Saints;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Though our wives will not joyne with us therein, or others in our familie, refuſe Communion with us,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yea though they ſhould reproach us for the ſame, as <hi>Michal mocked David</hi> for dancing before the Arke;
<note place="margin">2 Sam 6.20, 21, 22.</note> or though any of our Carnal kindred ſhould doe the like, we ſhould an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them reſolutely, as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Michal;</hi> If going to hear Sermons, or performing holy duties in and with my family (as prayer, reading the ſcripture, repeating Sermons <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) or in my cloſet alone, If theſe things <hi>make me vile, I will yet be more vile then thus.</hi> I will binde the reproaches I ſuffer for piety, purity, ſtrictneſs in duties, from my husband or wife, or from any of our friends to my forehead, and wear them as my crown; and they ſhall rather edge and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99599:35"/>ſpur me on thereto, then be any pull back or hindrance there from. Then a Husband hath a wife, as if he had none; and a wife hath a Husband as if ſhe had none.</p>
               <p>When we endeavour to ſerve God freely and intirely, and as much as we can, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, as if we were ſingle perſons, unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to any man or woman by Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; as if we had none but God to take care to ſerve, and pleaſe and approve our ſelves to: or as if we had none (related to us) to diſſwade or diſcourage us from the ſame. Or if we have relations and they ſhould attempt it, we are reſolved, that our God and our ſouls being dearer to us then they all, we will (by his grace) ſerve and pleaſe him, and tender the ſalvation of our ſouls, above them all, whether our husbands, or our wives, or kindred be pleaſed or diſpleaſed at it. Then we carry as if we did not mary.</p>
               <p>When we look at theſe two, to wit, the worſhipping of our dear Lord God; and the ſaving of our precious immortal Soules, as the main and ſupream buſines we have to do; and at Mariage but as ſubordinate and ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient thereunto: and but a ſecondary means of our good, when the deſire and purpoſe of our hearts is fixed upon three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Mariage Croſſes, and family cares and troubles,
<note place="margin">Luke 10.42.</note> ſhall not take us off from ſeeking the kingdom of God and the righteouſneſſe thereof,
<note place="margin">Iohn 6.27.</note> in the firſt place; the one thing need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; from chuſing the good part, that ſhall never be taken from us:
<note place="margin">2 not to our coming to Chriſt.</note> from labouring more for the meat that endureth, then for periſhing meat.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99599:36"/>
               <p n="2">2. That our relation ſhall not hinder us from coming unto <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt in his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances (as Word, Sacraments &amp;c.) when he invites us (and an opportunity is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation thereunto) It was the excuſe of one, bidden to the great ſupper, in <hi>Luc.</hi> 14 20. <hi>I have maried a wife,</hi> therefore <hi>I cannot come.</hi> Such an one hath a wife, ſo, as if he had none but a wife; neither a God to ſerve, nor a ſoul to ſave; as if a wife was <hi>ſummum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> the chief good. But he that hath a wife, as if he had none, will ſay, though I have maried a wife, that ſhall be no impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment to me, but I will come to Jeſus Chriſt in his Ordinances, and endeavour to bring my wife with me to Chriſt. However I will come, though ſhe hang back and will not come with me.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 That wee will go to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven alone hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-ward.</note> That if our Mariage do not help us God-ward and Chriſt-ward, it ſhall not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us; and that we will goe to Heaven alone (if our yoak-fellowes will not goe along with us) rather then to Hell with company.</p>
               <p>When theſe (and the like) are our reſolves and endeavours, then we have Husbands or wives as if we had none.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We that have wives may be as if we had none, by not ſuffering our Mariage to be a means of ſin unto us, either
<list>
                     <item>Immediately or</item>
                     <item>Mediately</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Inmediately in our ſelves, by breeding in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:99599:36"/>our hearts
<list>
                     <item>1 Either diſtruſt by reaſon, of the greatneſs of our charge, and ſmalneſs of our means.</item>
                     <item>2 Or diſcontent becauſe of the mani old troubles we meet with therein.</item>
                  </list> When we indeavour to overcome diſtruſt, and ſuppreſs diſcontent; and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruſt God for our families (to provide for them) as well, as for our ſingle ſelves, if we were alone: and to be as patient in bearing our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage Croſſes as our own perſonal trials; when we are content to take the better with the worſe, together, therein, and both as from the hand of God, as <hi>Job</hi> anſwered his wife, <hi>Shall we receive good at the hand of God, and ſhal we not receive evil?</hi> then we that have wives are as if we had none.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2 Let not Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage be a means of ſin to us.</note> 2. When we ſuffer not our mariage to be a means of ſin to us, Mediately by our yoak-fellowes being Inſtruments of Tentations to us unto ſin, to draw us from God and good.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To idolatry, ſuperſtition or will,
<note place="margin">1 Of Idolatry 1 Kings 11.4. Deut. 13 6, 8, 9.</note> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as <hi>Solomons wives turned away his heart after other Gods.</hi> Under the law an Enticer to Idolatry, though ſhe were the <hi>wiſe of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom,</hi> was to be put to death.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">2. Apoſtacy Job 2.9.</note>2 To Apoſtacy from God, or blaſphemy againſt God, to fall from integrity or ſted faſtneſs and, to think or ſpeak ill of God. <hi>Jobes</hi> wife tempted him thereunto, <hi>doeſt thou ſtill retain thy integrity? curſe God and die.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such like are the deſignes ſome wives have upon their Hutbands, to draw them from the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:99599:37"/>Truths, wayes and ordinances of God into errours, hereſies, by-wayes <hi>&amp;c,</hi> or licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Or to diſcourage their hearts from pious duties and courſes, as <hi>Michal</hi> ſought by her mocking to do unto <hi>David,</hi> from dancing before the ark.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 Injury</note> To Injury, to doe our neighbour wrong in taking (by unjuſt wayes) their houſe, land or goods from them, as <hi>Jezebel</hi> did <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard from him, for her Husband <hi>Ahab;</hi> to chear him up when he was ſick with grief and indignation, upon <hi>Naboths</hi> denial of his vineyard to him. <hi>Ahab</hi> deſired it, upon a valuable conſideration, but <hi>Jezebel</hi> his wife took the vineyard violently from <hi>Naboth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4 Any breach of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</note> by taking away his life.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Or to a breach of any (even the leaſt) of Gods commandments. <hi>Eve</hi> tempted her husband <hi>Adam</hi> to eat forbidden fruit (which was the tranſgreſſing of a law of Trial) hereby ſhe brought ſin and death upon her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and her Husband, and upon all their poſterity.</p>
               <p>Let this (by the way) be a caution to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to beware Satan do not abuſe them in making them his inſtruments or Agents, to entice or tempt their Husbands to any ſin, as pride, malice, revenge, vanity, covetouſneſs, or the like. Now, when we are alway watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and careful, leſt Satan ſhould ſurprize us by coming to tempt us unto ſin, in or by a conjugal Companion,
<note place="margin">Math. 16.22.23.</note> one ſo dear and near to us (lying in our boſomes) as he thinks we will ſuſpect no evil from, nor ſerpent in:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99599:37"/>(as Satan came to tempt Chriſt, in <hi>Peter</hi>) therefore we ponder well what counſel, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties, our propoſals are made to us by our yoak-fellowes, as well as by ſtrangers, which both <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> neglected to do. Or when they do perſwade or intice us to any evil whatſoever, either of Omiſſion or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, againſt God or man; we ſtrive, ſtrenuouſly to reſiſt all their ſuggeſtions, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and ſolicitations; and ſet our ſelves as a <hi>wall of braſs</hi> to repel them all, that they cannot prevail, no nor enter or peirce us. As <hi>Job</hi> not onely rejected his wifes perſwaſion, but gave her a ſharp reprehenſion for it. <hi>Thou ſpeakeſt as one of the fooliſh women,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely replied his wife <hi>Michals</hi> diſcourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcoff.</p>
               <p>Then we that have wives are as if we had none, and ye that have husbands are as if ye had none.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 Honor chriſt for your Husband.</note> We that have wives, or Husbands may be, as if we had none, by having Chriſt for the Husband of our ſouls, and by having holy fellowſhip with him, and by delighting our ſelves in him, in the embraces and ſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his love; and in the cheriſhing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts of his preſence. When Chriſt is dear to ours ſouls above all our relations (yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the world) and we are willing to leave father and mother, wife and children, houſe and lands, and all for Chriſt, that is,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To follow Chriſt in the Regeneration, as his diſciples: to follow the Lamb whither-ſoever he goeth, <hi>Revelat.</hi> 14.4.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:99599:38"/>
               <p n="2">2. To be willing to ſuffer the loſſe of all for Chriſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> did.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> To learn them all, to go to Chriſt, as beſt of all for us; then we have wives as if we had none. This Chriſt requires of all that would be his Diſciples; or be accounted worthy of him,
<note place="margin">Luc. 14.26.</note> even to hate father and mother, wife and children, that is to love them leſſe then him, and to be willing to leave them all for him. Hereto Chriſt makes a large promiſe of a hundred fold now in this time, and in the world to come eternal life, <hi>Mark,</hi> 10.29.30. <hi>Galeatius Caracciolus</hi> that Noble Marqueſs of <hi>Italy</hi> or rather the <hi>moſt Excelent Theophilus</hi>) did forſake parents and wife and children and all his friends and renounnced all his wealth and Dignitie becauſe (as he ſaid) he could not injoy both Chriſt and them. He was a rare example of leaving all (a very great all, of Relations, Poſſeſſions, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and pleaſures) for Chriſt, rather then to injoy all without Chriſt. Notwithſtanding the ſtrongeſt workings and wreſtlings of natural affections within him; and the powerfulleſt and moſt heart breaking Solicitations of his friends by prayer, Tears and Arguments to the Contrary; and the deep and ſore Agonies and Conflicts he had in himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; yet through the <hi>Grace</hi> of Chriſt, he overcame them all for Chriſt.</p>
               <p>A man may be ſaid to have a thing <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as an old houſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Garment) as if he had it not; when he hath ſomething of the ſame kind that is much better, as a new houſe to go unto or new cloathes to put on,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99599:38"/>when he pleaſeth. Now the ſoules Mariage with Chriſt is the moſt Excellent of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Conjunctions and Conſociations: it is the firſt and chiefeſt mariage in excellency, and thereof a Rule and pattern to humane mariage, to direct the due Carriage of the Parties each to other. To this purpoſe <hi>Paul</hi> propoſeth it in the fifth of the <hi>Epheſians.</hi> As a greater Light obſcures a leſs, ſo a greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light weans us from a leſs. If our ſouls be maried unto Chriſt, and take pleaſure in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt, this will wean us from our Temporal Mariage, and the delights of it, as poor low things of an inferiour nature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the body moſt which is the Earthly part of man. Senſual delights (wherein we partake with the beaſts) which cannot reach the ſublime part of man, the ſoul, to afford it divine refreſhments, which only Chriſt the Husband of it can do. This fellowſhip with Chriſt will abundantly compenſate or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, the loſs or want o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the comfort of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Relations; and take us off them, wean us from them, &amp; raiſe up our hearts above them. Even whileſt we have them. As it is in other things, when we make Grace our cheif goods, then we have Gold and ſilver as it we had it not; or Gods favour our chei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> honour; then we have the favour and honour of Men, as if we had it not. We have thing <hi>appretiatively</hi> and hold them <hi>tenaciouſly,</hi> when we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better then they, or ſo good: as the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous man hath his gold; the Ambitious man his Honor, the Voluptuous M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the Uxorious man his wife on
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:99599:39"/>whom he dotes: Theſe know or have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is better. A man cannot have an uſefull, delightfull Creature, as if he had it not, unleſs he have ſomething as good or better to injoye in the room thereof. When a man hath God to his portion, he may ſay, It is enough, though he hath nothing elſe. God without all, is a greater portion, then All without God. When Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>all in all</hi> to us; then all the comforts we have are as nothing to us, <hi>Scil.</hi> in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of Chriſt; then Mariage is nothing, wealth nothing, preferment nothing. When we have a better Husband for our ſouls (that is, Chriſt) then any Husband or wife is or can be for the body,
<note place="margin">4 Be ſober in all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, of Mariage. 1 Cor. 7.29.30.31.</note> ſhould not we upon this Account, who have wives or Husbands be as if we had none?</p>
               <p n="4">4. We that are maried may be as if we were not maried, by being very fober and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in all the effects, concomitants and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments of Mariage, which the Apoſtle par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularizeth in and connecteth with Mariage in the text, and in the thing; as ſorrow, joy, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions and wordly affairs and buſineſſes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending or circumſtantiating that condition.</p>
               <p>To be ſober and moderate in all theſe, and to be weaned or ſit looſe from them in our hearts (both which are included in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>i. e,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 in Mariage comfort.</note> as if not) is the way to have wives as if we had none.</p>
               <p>As 1. To be ſober and moderate in the uſe of all mariage comforts and delights; and in the fruits thereof, as the birth of children, or the like, and in our joy therein. <hi>This is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99599:39"/>as if we rejoyced not;</hi> not to overjoy our Mariage joyes.</p>
               <p>Not to be exceſſive or immoderate in any Mariage injoyment (or in our joy or delight therein) for that is to have a wife or a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, as if we had nothing beſides. As a man may be exceſs be a drunkard with his own drink, and a Glutton with his own meat, ſo likewiſe one may be unclean in the immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate uſe of the Mariage bed.
<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> on 7. com: 2 In Mariage grief.</note> What we are very moderate in, we uſe as if we uſed it not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To be moderate in our grief for the troubles that accompany mariage, as for the loſs of wife or children. The Jewes conceive that <hi>Abraham</hi> wept but a little for <hi>Sarahs</hi> death, or that his mourning for her was at leaſt not exceſſive but with Moderation,
<note place="margin">Ainſworth. Pareus.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.2. where its ſaid <hi>Abraham</hi> came to mourn for <hi>Sarah,</hi> and to weep for her, the word weep in the Hebrew hath one little letter extraordinary.</p>
               <p>David faſted and wept while his childe was yet alive; but when it died, <hi>why ſhould I weep any more</hi> ſaith <hi>David?</hi> when God took all <hi>Jobes</hi> children away at once with a ſtroke, <hi>he bleſſed the name of the Lord, Job.</hi> 1.21. This is to weep as if we wept not, not to overgrieve our mariage griefs:</p>
               <p n="3">3. To be moderate in,
<note place="margin">3 in worldly Matters.</note> and weaned from worldly Matters, which concerns mariage as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In Buying as if we poſſeſſed not; minding earthly things as if we minded them not. As a Traveller that goeth on in his way,
<note place="margin">as in buying.</note> and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99599:40"/>a labourer in his work, but both of them are in a deep ſtudy; and their mindes are intent upon other matters then either the journey of the one, or the work of the other. So ſhould our Mindes be Imployed about heavenly things (as much as may be) while we are going about wordly buſineſs. Things above ſhould have Our hearts, while our hands and feet are buſied about things below. We ſhould ſo deal in the world, as thoſe that are wholly taken off <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom the world.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.30.</note> This is <hi>to buy as if we poſſeſſed not</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as not to hold what we have bought or gotten too hard or cloſe to our ſelves or ours, as if we would keep all to our ſelves and part with nothing; for God hath many wayes to pluck our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes and poſſeſſions from us.
<note place="margin">Prov 23.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Riches make themſelves wings</hi> and can flee away from us, and our family and poſterity, as an Eagle. There is great uncertainty in them; this ſhould wean us from them.
<note place="margin">2. In uſing he world</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Uſing the world and the things of it as if we uſed it not, as <hi>food</hi> rayment, habitation and outward accomodations, (all which are appurtenances to mariage) to be very Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſober and moderate in them, and weaned from them; not ſetting our hearts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, nor being any way exceſſive or inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate in the uſe of them, is to uſe the word as if we uſed it not.
<note place="margin">1 Cor 7.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>A wiſe moderation in, and a holy Aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the matters of the world, may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther procure or preſerve and promote in us a Weanedneſs or fitting looſe from Temporal Relations; that we that have wives may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as though we had none.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99599:40"/>
               <p n="5">5. And laſtly,
<note place="margin">5. Enjoy rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to God.</note> we that have wives or hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands may be as if we had none, by Enjoying our Relations with Submiſſion to the will of God, for time and meaſure, how far and how long God pleaſeth to Continue them to us: and by labouring to get our ſpirits into ſuch a frame or poſture of preparation and readineſs, as freely and ſubmiſsively to part with Husband, wife, children, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne them up to God, when he takes them from us, or us from them;
<note place="margin">Acts. 21.14.</note> and to ſay obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entially, <hi>The will of the Lord be done.</hi> We have any thing as if we had it not, which we are willing to part with to God or for God: or elſe we oppoſe our wills to Gods will, as if we will have or keep perſons or things whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God will or no.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Objection.</hi> Parting with a dear yoke-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low is a great and ſad Trial, how may we be prepared for it?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7 Preparatives for the death of a yoak-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</note>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By ſerious and frequent Preconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe ſeven particulars; for when the the ſtroak is ſudden, it falls heavy; but when it is foreſeen, and we are forearmed and prepared, it may be more eaſily born.
<note place="margin">1. God hath a propriety in our Relations.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Let us conſider that God hath a ſpecial propriety in our Relations; my husband or my wife, and children are the Lords, by abſolute right, whilſt they are mine; yea more the Lords, then mine: God made and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied them for me, and gave them to me, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lent them for a Time, reſerving to himſelf his Intereſt in them. As he doth in all other Mercies, as he did in <hi>Iſraels</hi> Corn, wool, wine and flax. If God take husband,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.8.9.</note>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99599:41"/>or wife, or children away by death, he doth us no wrong,
<note place="margin">Math. 20.15.</note> for he requires no more but his own, <hi>Is it not lawful for God to doe what he will with his own?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job. 1.21.</note> Did not <hi>Job</hi> bleſs God upon this account when he took from him, what he gave to him? God hath given us ſo much Comfort and benefit in our Relations, and continued them ſo many years unto us; we ſhould rather be thankful to God, that we have injoyed them ſo long, then murmure or mourn too much, becauſe we muſt have them no longer.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2 Hope of their happines</note> Conſider we our hope of their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs dying in the Lord, that they are releaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wholly from all their pain ſorrow and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; and are gone home to their fathers houſe to inherit a kingdome prepared for them, and are now actually poſſeſſed of fulneſs of joy, and rivers of pleaſures, which ſhall endure for evermore. Therefore as Chriſt ſaid to his diſciples,
<note place="margin">John 14.28.</note> 
                  <hi>If ye loved me ye would rejoyce, becauſe I go to the father.</hi> So if we love husband, wife or children, we will rather rejoyce for their Gain by death, then mourn for our loſs of them; becauſe the one is far greater then the other. <hi>Paul</hi> would not have Chriſtians to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for their deceaſed friends (to wit imode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately) <hi>even as others which have no hope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.13.</note> to wit of their friends reſurrection and ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3 Hope of our going to them.</note> Conſider we, our hope of going to our dear Husbands, wives or children, who have got the ſtart of us, and are gone to Heaven before us: and of our fellowſhip with them there in that place of perfect joy, glory and felicity, where they and we ſhall meet one
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:99599:41"/>day, and never part more. This was <hi>Davids</hi> Comfort when his Childe died,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.23.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſhall goe to him, but he ſhall not return to me.</hi> This was <hi>Jacobs</hi> comfort at his death,
<note place="margin">Gen. 49.29.</note> 
                  <hi>I am to be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto my people,</hi> that is to my holy fathers and friends, or Saints, who are gone hence to their everlaſting reſt and joy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let us conſider that <hi>the time is ſhort.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">4 Shortneſs of Time. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1 Cor. 7.29.</note> It is a Metaphor from ſailes, which are wrapt up and contracted, when the ſhip draws neer harbours.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1 Of life.</note> The time of life is ſhort and uncertain, neither Husband nor wife knowes, how long, or rather how little a while they ſhall yet live together, or enjoy one another; or how ſoon death may ſtep between them and part them. The conſideration hereof</p>
               <p n="1">1. Should quicken us, both to diligence and expedition in all duties of our Vocation, general and particular, and of our Relations, becauſe we have much work to doe, and but a little time to do it in; and a loſſe of time may bring great grief and miſery upon us. Some that have lain a dying would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a world for time to repent, believe and ſerve God in. I have heard (ſaith a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend man) ſome crying day and night, call time again; but time paſt is irrevocable and irrecoverable.</p>
               <p>This ſhould alſo quicken Husband and wife to preparation for parting one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This conſideration may alſo comfort us, that if the one party be taken away by death, the other may follow ſoon after, or
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:99599:42"/>not ſtay long behind, and ſo both may meet in Heaven, they know, not how ſoon.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2. Of Peace.</note> The time of Peace may be ſhort. Troubleſome times may come (tribulations and perſecutions) all outward Comforts may be clouded in a day; and they may be violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pulled one from other. Will it not be a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy either to husband or wife to be taken away from the evils to come? and may not the Surviver of them, when ſingle, perhaps ſhift bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for him or her ſelf. This was <hi>Pauls</hi> reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Corithians</hi> Queſtion about mariage,
<note place="margin">In 1 Cor. 7.</note> that for thoſe that were not maried, it were good and expedient to keep them ſo, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>The preſent distreſs, ver.</hi> 26. that is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of Chriſtians at that time; for they were compelled by the <hi>Roman</hi> Tyrants and Pagans to fly with their wives and children for preſervation of their lives; and to flie from place to place, as <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> did, to ſeek ſafety where they could find it. As for thoſe that were already maried, he gives them this counſel, <hi>Let them that have wives be as if they had none</hi> &amp;c. Times of perſecution or of publick calamitie may make a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between husband and wife. It's their wiſdome to prepare before hand for parting the one with the other. For this is one part of their preparation againſt evil Times.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <note place="margin">5. Mixture of groſſes.</note> Let us conſider the Mixture of Croſſes, Troubles and ſorrowes with comforts and refreſhments in our matrimonial ſtate; and many times the former weighs down the latter. God layes the ſame as wormewood
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99599:42"/>upon the breſts of mariage, to wean us from it; and make us more willing (then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we would be) to part with our yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellow; as alſo to endear unto us, both our fellowſhip with Chriſt, which is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſweet, and no bitterneſs in it; and Heaven, where there is all joy without any Sorrow at all.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <note place="margin">6. The ineffica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of ſorrow.</note> Let us Conſider the inefficacy of immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate ſorrow for the death of husband, wife, or children, for we can contribute nothing by our Tears to their felicity, if they die in the Lord; or if not, we cannot mitigate their pain or miſery thereby. All our Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, cannot revive or recover them. Upon this ground <hi>David</hi> ceaſed mourning when his child died. Why ſhould I weep any more? as if he had ſaid, It is to no purpoſe, <hi>Can I bring him back again?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.23.</note> We may ſay of Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate grief in this Caſe what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid of Mirth, <hi>what doth it?</hi> It can doe our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed friends no good: It may do us much hurt; by weakening our bodies and ſadning our ſpirits ſo much, as to deprive us of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in our lives and livelyhoods, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able or indiſpoſe us for duties.</p>
               <p>It is beſt for us to do in this as in other caſes, when God doth things croſſe or contrary to our deſires or expectations, even to reſolve our wills into Gods will, and ſubmit to it patiently and acquieſs in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">7. God can ſupply the loſs.</note> The ſeventh and laſt particular Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to prepare us for parting with a dear vokefellow is this, God can ſupply our loſs (by death) of a loving Husband, or of a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99599:43"/>helpful wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, or of hopeful children, either</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1 Mediately.</note> Mediately, by giving us another hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or wife, fitted for us, and fitted with like gifts and graces, to equal if not exceed the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, or by rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing up ſome friends or others to be very helpful and comfortable to us in our Solitary condition, when God by death hath taken away our deareſt companion from us, and we are left alone.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2. Or Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.</note> Or Immediately by himſelf; He is the fountain of all goodneſs; and hath all that Love, kindneſs, delight, comfort, help in him ſelf; that is or can be in a husband or wife, or in any other Relation, yea and infinitely more; more then is in all the husbands, and wives in the world; more then they can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly contain, becauſe God is Infinite, as in his eſſence ſo in all goodneſs; and they are finite and ſhallow veſſels, but of a ſmal quantity, and hold but little. When God takes away my wife or my husband or my childe from me, I may boldly ſeek to him, truſt in him, and expect from him, not onely inward ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, but the Comfort and help of my yoke fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low or child that is dead. The Lord can, and I hope will, be better to me then ten Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands or wifes; or then a hundred children The Lord is able out of his wiſdome and goodneſs, and by the comforts of his preſence, to make an abundant ſupply and reparation of the loſs we ſuſtain by the death of our dear yoke-fell wes or any friend, with this Addition, that <hi>the Lord liveth,</hi> and ſhall doe for ever, though Husband or wife or friends dye. What are our Relations but pitchers
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99599:43"/>or Conduit-pipes to convey comfort and help from God unto us: when the Pitcher is broken we ſhould go to the fountain. <hi>Dulcius Ex ipſo fonte.</hi> Waters drink ſweeteſt there. God gave us all the comfort of our Relations at firſt, and if he take them from us, he is able abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to make a ſupply, either by other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures or out of himſelf. <hi>Nihil dat quod non habet,</hi> When a Husband dies &amp; leaves his poor wife and children to the wide world, and hath nothing in the world to leave them, then God ſaith to him, <hi>Leave thy father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe children, I will preſerve them alive, and Let thy widow truſt in me:</hi> q. d. I will take the charge and care of them. I will provide for them. I will be a Husband to the widow, and a father to the fatherleſs. God hath given many precepts and made many promiſes concerning widowes and, orphans, proviſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, protectional and conſolational.</p>
               <p>Let me adde this by way of caution, we ſhould take heed our affections be not inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately ſet upon any of our Relations, be it a wife or a husband or a childe, that we do not love them too well, or delight in them too much, or dote on them, or make Idols of them, for this may juſtly provoke God to take them from us, or to try us ſadly in them. Whereas the way to keep them, is to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with them, out of ſubmiſſion to God, who gave them to us, and whoſe they ſtill are, and who is worthy to be ſerved with his own. Becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with his onely Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to a difficult command of God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99599:44"/>he injoyed him with a ſpecial bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16, 17. <hi>Mr. Burroughes</hi> in his expoſition on <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.9. relates a remarkable ſtorie from his owne knowledge, that a Godly man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring his friends to meet to bleſſe God for his bleſſings in a plentiful harveſt; after dinner was done, a little Childe comes in, who was indeed very lovely, oh, ſaith the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I am afraid I ſhall make a God of this Childe: by and by the Childe was miſſing, and preſently they went to look him, and he was found ſprawling drowned in a Pond. Conſider this ye Parents (ſaith <hi>Mr. Burroughes</hi>) who have your hearts inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately ſet on your children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:99599:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>QUAERE.</hi> Whether is it lawful for a man to mary his wives own ſiſter?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer</hi> IT is Unlawful, which I prove by ſix Arguments,</p>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi> Argument.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>A man may not marry one that is near of kin to him.</item>
                     <item>A mans wives ſiſter is near of kin to him.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ergo,</hi> A man may not mrary his wives ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi> A man may not marry one that is near of kin to him: for that is Gods precept or Rule for Mariage, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.6. <hi>None of you ſhall approach</hi> to wit in a Conjugal way) <hi>unto any that is near of kin to him.</hi> or to any kindred of his fleſh, or to any of his fleſh, or to any fleſh of his fleſh: as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Hebrew word may be rendered,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> for it ſignifieth both fleſh and kindred.</p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:99599:45"/>
                  <p>This law commands that a juſt and due Diſtance be obſerved and preſerved (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of blood and alliance) by perſons that would contract Matrimony; that neither of them do come near the kindred of thier fleſh.</p>
                  <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w kindred (as appears by the Catalogue of Particulars inſtanced, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. from the 7. <hi>verſe</hi> to 19.) is not onely <hi>Conſanguinity,</hi> whereby Perſons are of a blood, but <hi>Affinity</hi> alſo, whereby they that are not of blood, are allyed by Mariage each to other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Houſhold go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> Yet Affinity or Alliance growes (as <hi>Mr. Perkins</hi> ſaith) by Mixtion or Participation of blood in the coupling of man and wife to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in lawful mariage.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. But a mans wives Siſter is near of kin to him, becauſe</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Brother and Siſter (whether by Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinitie or Affinity) are next of kin in a Collateral Line; therefore Mariages bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them are unlawful, and inceſtuous.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. She relates to him in the firſt degree of Affinity.
<note place="margin">Doctor Halls caſes.</note> Out of our Civilians and Canon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts a Learned Author that writes of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject gathers</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Kinds or degrees of Affinity Primary and Secondary.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi rend="margQuotes">Primary, is that Affinity between the Husband and Couzins of blood to his wife, or <hi>eConverſo:</hi> which indeed is juſtly held no leſſe for a barre of Mariage then his own natural Conſanguinity: for that is an Affinity contracted upon intereſt of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99599:45"/>blood, by vertue of that intire union between man and wife whereby they two become one fleſh.</hi> Upon this Account a mans wives Siſter comes to be the kindred of his fleſh: and therefore Gods Law prohibits him to marry her.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="margQuotes">The Second degree of Affinity is where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is another perſon added to that firſt kind now mentioned. Here the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity ariſeth onely from the intereſt of an Affinity formerly contracted;</hi> not upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of blood, as the former kind doth.</p>
                  <p>Mariage within this Second Degree is queſtioned; as whether it be Lawful for a man to marry his wives Brothers widow; by ſome that are the moſt favourable, it is held unmeet and inconvenient, (though lawful) as coming over near to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erge</hi> of a ſinful Conjunction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> for perſons to marry within the firſt degree of Affinity (as for a man to marry his wives Siſter) cannot but be unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably unlawful.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>2. Argument.</head>
                  <p>A man may not marry any of his wives kindred nearer in blood, then he may of his own. But a man may not marry his own Siſter, <hi>Ergo,</hi> a man may not marry his wives own Siſter.</p>
                  <p>A man may not marry any of his wives kindred, nearer in blood then he may of his own: nor the woman of her husbands kindred, nearer in blood then of her own.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are the very Termes in the Conteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith, ſet forth by the Aſſembly of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99599:46"/>Divines, <hi>Proximity of alliance is no leſſe a barre to Mariage, then proximity of blood.</hi> For this I will give two Reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Reaſ. 1.</note> Becauſe of what degree any one is of Conſanguinity to the wife, in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of affinity is that perſon to the wives husband.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>De ſpenſalibus.</hi> Of houſhol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> government <hi>p.</hi> 677.</note> This Rule is laid down by <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> and by <hi>Mr. Perkins</hi> alſo, who addes further (to recite his own words)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Couzias by Mariage within the degrees both of the right and Collateral Line, doe come near to the kindred of their fleſh, in the ſame manner that Couzins by blood doe in the ſame Line; and the like degrees in both are forbidden.</hi> From hence it may be gathered (ſaith he) that <hi>it is in no ſort lawfull for a man when his wife is dead to marry her Siſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence it is laid down as a certain Rule among Divines, <hi>Cujus non licet inire Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias ejus nec conjugis licet.</hi> Becauſe a wife cannot marry her owne Brother, nor a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band his own Siſter; no more can a man marry his wives own Siſter, becauſe her near conſanguine who was one fleſh with him.</p>
                  <p>This Rule holds undeniably true within the firſt ranck of aſſinity, which is a perpetual Impediment to marriage: as though the wiſe be dead, yet her kindred is of affinity ſtill with her husband remaning alive. The Rights and T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of affinity between the Husband and the Conſanguines of the wife are not looſed, the wiſe being dead, although they had no children together; but they hold firm ſtill, being founded in the union made between them by Mariage, not in Iſſue,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99599:46"/>though that may ſtrengthen the ſame. See for this <hi>Willets Synopſis Papiſmi page</hi> 790. <hi>Junij Append. and Explic. Levit. Theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2
<note place="margin">Reaſ. 2. <hi>De ſpenſalibas</hi> Theſ. 5. p. 788.</note> Becauſe by the very ſame Rules, ſaith <hi>Zanchius,</hi> is a husband forbiden to marry with the Conſanguines of his wife (or with thoſe that are of her blood) that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguines or thoſe of a blood are forbidden to marry among themſelves. But a man may not marry his own Siſter, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.9 therefore nor his wives Siſter.</p>
                  <p>The Reſult is this. A man may as lawfully marry his own mother as his wives mother, and his own Aunt (by father or mother) as his Uncles wife, for that is ſaid to be an <hi>uncovering of the nakedneſs of his fathers Brother, Levit.</hi> 18.14. and his own Siſter as his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife, for this is called an <hi>uncovering of his brothers Nakedneſs, Levit.</hi> 18 16. or as his wives Siſter. From both which being compared together I may frame the</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>3. <hi>Argument.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A man may not marry his Brothers wife, <hi>Ergo</hi> he may not marry his Wives Siſter.</p>
                  <p>A man may not marry his Brothers wife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this is Expreſly forbidden in <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.16. and 20.21. Therefore nor his wives Siſter becauſe a mans wives Siſter is full as near of kin to him as his B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>others wife is and where there is the ſome Reaſon of propir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<note place="margin">Ameſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>App<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </note> there is the ſame Reaſon and force of prohil it on. It is <hi>Dr. Anes</hi> his Rule, In thoſe degre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s (prohibited to mariage.) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99599:47"/>not expreſſed in the law ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, if they have the ſame nearneſs, with thoſe which are by Name forbidden. As the ſame law that, forbids the Nephew to marry the Aunt, forbids the Uncle to marry the Neece, <hi>Levit</hi> 18.14. and <hi>cap.</hi> 20.20 An Uncles wife and an Aunts husband are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly near of kin,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide Annot. in Lev.</hi> 18.14, <hi>Zanch de ſponſ. Theſ.</hi> 4.</note> but for a man to marry his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles wife is under an Expreſs prohibition; ſo is it for a woman to marry her Aunts husband. It is truly ſaid by <hi>Dr. Hall</hi> in his Caſes of Conſe. <q>Divers no leſs unlawful Copulations are omitted in this black roll of uncleanneſſes then thoſe which are expreſly mentioned; the reſt being i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tended to come in by way of Analog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> onely; for it is eaſie to obſerve that all the ſeveralties of the degrees pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited run ſtill upon the male, under which, if the Exorbitancies of the other ſex were not meant to be comprehended, females ſhould be lawleſs and the law im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore though a mans marrying his wives Siſter be not forbidden in Expreſs T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rms, yet it is effectually prohibited by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Analogy and clear Implication of ſence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>4. <hi>Argument.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>A woman may not marry two Brothers.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ergo,</hi> a man may not marry two Siſters.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Becauſe there is the ſame Reaſon of propin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity (or nearneſs of kin) in both: and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99599:47"/>requires this (ſaith <hi>Beza.</hi>)
<note place="margin">De Repudiis &amp; Divortiis.</note> 
                     <hi>ut de ſimilibus ſimiliter ſtatuatur,</hi> that the like ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined of the like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It was a Canon in the <hi>Neocaeſarien</hi> Councel, that it a woman mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two Brothers, <hi>abjiciatur uſque ad mortem,</hi> ſhe ſhould be caſt off even to death.</p>
                  <p>Here I will anſwer the chief objections which I conceive may be made.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Object.</hi> This prohibition of degrees from mariage mentioned in <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. was but ſome Moſaical law given to the <hi>Jewes</hi> onely, and not binding to us <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, the laws there expreſt againſt ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous Mariages from <hi>ver.</hi> 6 to 19. (as well as againſt adultery, <hi>Sodomy,</hi> Buggery in the verſes following) are moral, univerſal and perpetual, binding to all Nations, by which the law of Nature is Explained. So ſaith <hi>Willet</hi> in his <hi>Synopſ. Papiſ.</hi> pag. 790. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſins Catech. qu.</hi> 109. <hi>Pet. Mart. Loc. Com. Ameſ. Caſ. Conſe. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 35. <hi>Zanchius, Perkins</hi> and diverſe others. See the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith</hi> by the Aſſembly of Divines chap. 24.</p>
                  <p>That theſe prohibitions are moral and Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral may be proved by five Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Elſe, why doth God count the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of theſe lawes ſuch <hi>abominations, Levit.</hi> 1826. and <hi>abominable Cuſtomes,</hi> ver. 30. which defile the land, verſ. 25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Elſe, why ſhould the breaches of thoſe lawes be charged upon the Heathen the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and Canaanites (that is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that dwelt in the land of <hi>Canaan</hi>)
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99599:48"/>as their abominable practices, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.3.24.27, 30. <hi>ver. In all theſe are the Nations defiled,</hi> and they were ſeverely puniſhed for the ſame. For theſe ſins (even of inceſtuous Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages among the reſt) the land of <hi>Canaan did ſpue out her Inhabitants</hi> though Gentiles (<hi>v.</hi> 25.) who were not tied to obſerve the lawes peculiar to the Hebrews: yea who had not the law written in Tables of ſtone. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe ſins of the Gentiles were ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of Nature.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Willet</hi> in Lev. 18. qu. 30.</note> It is ſaid of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nites that they were guilty of many other ſins; but moſt of all they were defiled by theſe Pollutions of the fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh <hi>and Vncovering of Nakedneſs,</hi> which they learned of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Cham</hi> and <hi>Canaan,</hi> who conſented to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to leave uncovered their fathers Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> 3. Elſe, why were the Jewes forbidden and forewarned of theſe ſins, to wit, Inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mariages.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As being the Manners of the Heathen among whom they had lived and converſed in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and were to live and converſe with in <hi>Canaan,</hi> or as being the ſins of the Gentiles, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.3. <hi>After the doings of the land of Egypt, wherein ye dwelt, and after the doing, of the land of Canaan whither I bring you, ſhall ye not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi> Theſe were their doings.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And that under the very ſame penalty God inflicted on the <hi>Canaanites</hi> for theſe ſins, <hi>ver.</hi> 28, 29. <hi>that the land ſpue not you alſo, when you defile it (to wit, by an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of theſe abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſpued out the Nations that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</hi> God concludes with this charge
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99599:48"/>to <hi>Iſrael</hi> ver. 30. <hi>Therefore ſhall ye keep mine Ordinance, that ye commit not any of theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ble cuſtomes, which were committed before you, and that ye defile not your ſelves therein. I am the Lord your God.</hi> God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth many and heavy judgements upon the breach of theſe lawes, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.11.12.14.16, 20. <hi>Deut,</hi> 27 20.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> 4. That theſe Prohibitions are moral may further appear becauſe we find them upon the ſame account not onely in Moſes but in the prophets; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.10.11. <hi>Amos</hi> 2.7. not onely preſcribed in the old Teſtament, but preſſed in the new; as, that it is not lawful to have a <hi>Fathers wiſe</hi> (or mother in law) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. Yea, or a <hi>Brothers wife, Mark</hi> 6.18.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> 5. Inceſtuous Mariages are prohibited by the light of nature and from her principles. For to this purpoſe (ſaith <hi>Mr. Perkins</hi>) not onely the lawes of the Romane Emperours (which according to <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Loc. Com. claſſ. 2. c. 10. Num. 43.</note> were accounted <hi>inter egregias &amp; honeſtiſſimas (ab honeſtate naturae deſumptas, Zanchi.)</hi> amongſt the moſt honeſt and famous lawes) but alſo the civil Canons and conſtitutious of men (very skilful in that kind) have in all ages been made expreſly againſt ſuch perſons as have offended in thoſe Societies (or Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) forbidden by the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now whatſoever Law is natural being written in the hearts of Heathens, muſt needs be moral and perpetual, as it is written in Gods Book at large in a full and fair copy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj</hi> 2. God commanded <hi>Deut.</hi> 25, 5. that the Brother in caſe his Brother died without iſſue
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99599:49"/>ſhould take his wife and raiſe up ſeed to him, <hi>Ergo,</hi> its lawful to mary a Brothers wife, and why not then a wives ſiſter?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> That Prohibition in <hi>Lev.</hi> 18.16. of marying the Brothers wife, is the law of nature common to all Nations. This in <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.5. is but a ſpecial exception of a general Law; a peculiar priviledge granted by God (the Law maker) to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who was pleaſed then (as he might) to make this particular exception from it among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and that in a ſpecial caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve families and inheritances in that land, which God would have diſtinct among them for the Meſſiah's ſake, that it might be known clearly of what tribe he came. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Family in the name of the firſt born. This being but an indulgence (granted to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in a ſpecial caſe and by a ſpecial warrant; or if a law, yet but judicial appropriated to their ſtate, and relating to the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Meſſiah) is not now lawful to be preached by us <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whom the caſe doth not at all concern; but we are under the general prohibition in <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.16. which is fully confirmed in the Goſpel, <hi>Mark.</hi> 6.18. <hi>John ſaid unto Herod, It is not lawful for thee to have thy Brothers wife.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. <hi>Jacob</hi> maried two Siſters <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leah,</hi> Therefore a man may marry his wives Siſter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> The examples of the Patriarches (or others) who tranſgreſs the Rule, may not be imita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, nor be made a Rule. Wherein ſoever
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99599:49"/>they turn aſide we muſt leave them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a better guid, that is the law of God, the Rule of Gods word. As many as walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Rule (and not according to Examples ſwerving from it) <hi>peace and mercy ſhall be upon them. Gal</hi> 6.16. <hi>Cain,
<note place="margin">Factum eſt compellente ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate. Auguſt.</note> Eno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h</hi> and <hi>Seth</hi> maried their own Siſters; neceſſity made it then not unlawful. It is a juſt Rule of Law <q>Thoſe things may not be drawn into pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent which have been yielded upon meer neceſſity.</q>
                     <note place="margin">Doctor Halls ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> As we uſe to ſay, neceſſity hath no Law, ſo it can make none. After wards as mankind grew, nature it ſelfe taught men to keep further aloof from their <hi rend="margQuotes">own fleſh: and ſtill remeteneſs of diſtance enlarged it ſelf with time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. The marying of a wives Siſter is not directly forbidden in the law; and what is not prohibited is permitted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> The marying of a mans own daughter is not expreſly forbidden in <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. (but of his ſons daughter or daughters daughter <hi>ver.</hi> 10. or of his daughter in law, <hi>ver.</hi> 15.) is it therefore lawful?</p>
                  <p>There are inceſtuous Mariages not ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which are as really forbidden as thoſe which are expreſſed. If we hold our ſelves cloſe to the letter of this Rule, that what is not prohibited is permitted it will lead us into <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> But this Objection received its anſwer before in the third Argument.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Fifth</hi> Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ames caſe Conſ. lib.</hi> 5.</note>For a man to mary his wives Siſter, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders one end of Mariag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, which is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latation
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99599:50"/>of kindred and affection;
<note place="margin">Junii Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plan. Levit.</note> that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society might be extended and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by a Matrimonial conjunction, between families that were remote and diſ-joyned: That is a good note and to purpoſe, which our Divines have in their <hi>Annotations</hi> on <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>What in this Law (<hi>viz.</hi> againſt Inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mariages) is forbidden to the <hi>Jews,</hi> is much more forbidden to Chriſtians; who having more latitude and liberty of choice then they had (who were to marry not onely within their own Nation, but within their own Tribe, and ſometimes (as hath been ſaid) two Brothers muſt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively be Husbands to one wife) are leſs capable of excuſe, if in carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence they tranſgreſſe theſe prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions. And in the general (ſince the Goſpel is the Law of love and charity, not to one Nation onely, but all the world over) as far as conſanguinity or affinity will work in affection without a new tye of Matrimony, ſo far reacheth matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial prohibition; and ſhould there firſt begin where the Relations are ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, that they have little or no operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of love: that ſo charity might be more diffuſive; and not ſo contracted to ones kindred, as it was among the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>The <hi>Sixth</hi> Argument</head>
                  <p>May be drawn from humane Teſtimonies, (which challenge a place after Scripture and Reaſon) that paſſe their condemnatory ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99599:50"/>upon this Mariage, <hi>viz.</hi> of a man with his wives ſiſter: as</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Laws made againſt it. <hi>Zanchy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theſ. 5. circa incepta conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia inter Affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> in his book <hi>de Sponſalibus</hi> ſaith, This is <hi>Moſes</hi> his ſenſe, and therefore the Law of Nature, that it is as filthy and diſhoneſt a thing for one man to mary two ſiſters one after another: as for one woman to marry 2. brothers one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. And this, ſaith he, is confirmed by thoſe Laws of the <hi>Romanes</hi> (which are by all judged to be taken from the honeſty of Nature) and bypious and Chriſtian Emperors; who do as well condemn the Inceſt that a man ſhould mary his wives ſiſter, as that he ſhould marry his brothers wife. And though ſome of the <hi>Romanes</hi> did marry ſo, as <hi>Lucius Tarquinius Superbus</hi> did his Brothers wife, and <hi>Honorius</hi> the Emperour did two ſiſters. Yet <hi>Dion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſius</hi> calls the former mariage <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> an impious mariage; a thing abominable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Graecians</hi> and <hi>Barbarians:</hi> And the latter was condemned: and the unhappy end of both the ſiſters (as he relates) declared that thoſe Mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges (<hi>vis.</hi> of two ſiſters) were not allowed of God.</p>
                  <p>That Table of forbidden degrees in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſet forth by Authority, names this expreſſly, the wives ſiſter. And the laws of the Land prohibit this mariage. See Sr. <hi>Edward Cooks</hi> ſecond part of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> page 683. See the Statute of the twenty and fifth year of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, chap. 22. and of his twenty and eighth year, c. 9. and of his thirty and ſecond year, c. 38.</p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:99599:51"/>
                  <p n="2">2. As for the ancient Fathers, <hi>Patres omnes haſce nuptias damnarunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Zanchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> All the fathers condemned theſe mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. So do our moderne Divines generally make the Siſter of a mans wife to be an affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hindring mariage as <hi>Junius</hi> in his notes and table of degrees upon <hi>Levit.</hi> 18. and the Geneva Divines in their notes and table upon the ſame chapter. <hi>Beza de Repud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is et Divortiis</hi> is full and expreſs againſt it, <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>Polanus</hi> in his <hi>Syntagma l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 53. <hi>Butanus de Conjugio Loc.</hi> 12. <hi>Willets Comment on Levit.</hi> 18. <hi>Quaeſt.</hi> 17.</p>
                  <p>Yea learned <hi>Zanchie</hi> affirmes that <hi>Noſtri feculi doctiſſimus quiſque ejuſdem eſt ſententiae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">lsc. cit.</note> all the moſt learned of his time were of the ſame opinion; and that his poſition (<hi>viz.</hi> For a man to marry his wives Siſter is in ceſt) is confirmed by the conſent of all <hi>Graeciaus</hi> and <hi>Barbarians</hi> and Nations.</p>
                  <p>I will conclude with the grave advice ſome Divines have given about the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of <hi>Couzen</hi> Germanes; which holds more ſtrongely in the caſe propoſed.</p>
                  <p>One ſaith <q>Let ſingle perſons who have the world before them look further of, and faſten their affections at a more unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able diſtance.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Another ſaith, <q>It is ſafe to forbear what is doubtful, and to keep aloof from what is unlawful; eſpecially the choice of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful marlages being large enough, without the hazzard of ſo great a ſinne as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:99599:51"/>
                  <p>It was wont to be Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to this purpoſe,</p>
                  <p>Let thoſe who muſt walk cloſe to the brim of a ſteep precipice look well to their feet, and tread ſure; but if a man be to chuſe his way, let him ſo caſt it, as that he may not approach near the brink of danger.</p>
                  <closer>The Lord give us underſtanding in all things, and guide our feet in his wayes.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
